[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi, I'm Adam Porter and this is
Programming Mobile Applications
for Android Handheld systems In addition
to the query method, some common content
resolver
methods include: the delete, insert and
update methods.
The delete method takes three parameters,
a U.R.I. specifying the data to be
deleted, a string specifying a pattern for
selecting which rows to delete.
And another array of strings, providing
arguments for that selection pattern.
This method returns the number of rows
that were deleted.
The insert method takes a URI indicating
the data
set into which you want to insert a new
row.
It also takes an object of the content
values
type, which holds the fields for that new
row.
And this method returns the URI of the
newly inserted row.
And the update method also takes a URI
and a content values object, just like
Insert did.
But like the delete method, it also takes
a string selection pattern and an
array of selection string arguments; for
indicating which specific rows to update.
And this method returns the number of rows
that were updated
Our next example application is called
content provider insert contacts.
This application reads several contacts
from the Android contacts content
provider.
And it then inserts several new contacts
into that content provider.
And then displays the old and the new
contacts.
And finally, when the application exits,
it deletes all these new contacts.
Let's run this application.
[SOUND].
So here's my device.
And now I'll start the content provider
insert contacts application.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
As you can see, this application is
displaying a single button labeled Insert
Contacts.
I'll hit the Home button now and start the
People application.
Now here, you can see some contacts that I
have on this device.
Okay, now let me quit out of this
application And now I'll restart
our sample application, and again you can
see the Insert Contacts button.
When I hit this button, some new contacts
will be inserted into the contacts content
provider.
So, here it goes.
And here you can see that I've inserted
four new contacts into the contacts
content provider.
Now just to be sure let me hit
the home button again and restart the
people application.
Now as you can see, the application does
indeed Show those
new contacts that we programmatically
inserted into the contacts content
provider.
So that means that other applications can
see, display, and even modify these new
contacts.
Let's look at the source code for this
application.
So here's the application open in the IDE.
Now I'll open the main activity.
In OnCreate, the code first gets
information
about the accounts registered on this
device.
Next the code calls the insert all new
contacts method, which inserts the four
new contacts.
And after this, the code sets up and uses
a
Cursor Loader to get and display the
appropriate contact information.
Let's look at how this application inserts
the new contacts.
The Insert All New Contacts method sets up
a batch operation.
In which it inserts all of the new
contacts at once.
And so it starts by creating an array list
of content provider operations.
And it then calls the Add Record to Batch
insert operation method for each of the
new contacts.
Now in this method, the code first
adds some information to the raw contacts
table,
such as the account's name and type, and
the fact that this contact should be
starred.
Which means it's treated as a favorite
contact.
Next, the method adds the new contact's
name to the data table.
And after all the new contacts have been
added to the batch operation, the insert
all new contacts method then called the
applied
batch method to commit the entire batch
operation.
Finally, if you want to create your own
content
provider, then you'll need to do the
following things.
First, implement a storage system for the
data.
And you'll often do this by creating an
SQL Lite database,
but as we'll see later, other approaches
will adjust just as well.
Next, you 'll define what is called a
Contract Class.
That defines constants and other
information that other applications
will need in order to use your Content
Provider.
After that, you going to define a Content
Provider subclass,
implementing for example, methods such as
delete and insert.
And finally, you'll declare and configure
your Content Provider.
In the AndroidManifest.xml file for its
application.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Our next example application is called
Content Provider Custom.
This application defines a content
provider for simple ID and string pairs.
Let's first take a look at the source code
for this application.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So here's the content provider custom
application open in the IDE.
First I'll open up the content provider
itself.
And this is in the strings content
provider.java file.
Here you can see that this class extends
the content provider class.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now first you can see that the actual data
is
stored in a simple data structure of the
type SparseArray.
So your content provider doesn't always
have to be implemented using a database.
Next the code defines a number of methods.
First, there's the delete method.
Now, this method removes either a single
record from
the database or it removes all of the
records.
In addition this method doesn't process
any of the SQL constructs.
Now this method tests to see whether the
URI.
That was passed in, refers to the whole
table or to a single record within the
table.
And if it refers to the whole table, then
the code clears the entire sparse array.
And if it refers to only a single record,
then
the code removes that single record from
the sparse array.
[SOUND].
And lastly the code returns the number of
records that were deleted.
Next the code implements the get type
method, this method uses the data
contract class to return the mime type of
the data associated with a
given U.R.I. Next, the code implements the
insert method.
This method extracts the data for a given
record, puts it in the
data record object, and then stores the
data record object in the sparse array.
Finally, it returns a new URI that can be
used to retrieve this new record.
Next the code implements the query method.
This method begins by creating a matrix
cursor object, now this is just a
simple cursor that will return all of the
data associated with each record.
And continuing on, if the URI refers to
all of the records, the code will insert
every record into this cursor If instead
the URI refers to a
single record then the code will add only
that record to the cursor.
And finally the code returns the cursor it
just created.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The last method is oncreate and normally
you would initialize the data storage
system here.
But for this simple example, no
initialization is necessary, the code
simply returns true to indicate that the
initialization completed properly.
And before we move on, let's open up
the Android manifest xml file for this
application.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Here you can see that we've added a
provider tag.
And within this tag, we've specified the
name
of the class that implements this content
provider.We've added
the authority portion of the URI that will
have to be used to access this content
provider.
And we've set the exported attribute to
true
to allow other applications to access this
content provider.
Our last example application is called
ContentProviderCustomUser.
This application is separate from the
content
provider custom application that we just
looked at.
However, it reads data from that content
provider and displays the records in a
ListView.
Let's look at this application in action.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So here's my device.
Now I'll start up the content provider
custom user application.
And as you see, the application displays
two data records.
Let's look at the source code for this
application to see where that data came
from.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So here's the content provider custom user
application open in the IDE.
Now I'll open up the main activity.
The oncreate method begins by getting a
reference to the content resolver for this
context.
Next, it creates a content values object.
After that, the code adds a value for
record one.
And then calls the insert method to insert
that record into the content provider.
The code then does the same thing for a
second, and a third record.
And then, it deletes the first record that
it had previously inserted, by calling the
delete method.
And after all of this, the code then
queries
the content provider to extract all of the
records
that are currently stored in the content
provider and
then it displays those records in a list
view.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So that's all for our lesson on
ContentProviders.
Please join me next time for a discussion
of
the last fundamental component of Android,
the service class.
Bye for now.
[BLANK_AUDIO]