Hi, I'm Adam Porter, and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
As I said before, Android also allows
applications to write to external memory.
One extra twist that you'll need to
consider however, when
you do this, is that external memory can
be removable.
For example, when it's provided by an SD
card.
And because of this, that media can appear
or disappear without warning.
And therefore, when your application is
going to write to external
memory, you'll first need to determine the
state of the external memory.
Now one way to do that is
by using the environment class's
getExternalStorageState Method.
That method will return a value indicating
the current state of the device's external
memory.
And some of those values are shown here,
for example, there's MEDIA_MOUNTED, which
means that the media is present and that
it's mounted with read and write access.
There's MEDIA_MOUNTED_READ_ONLY, which
means that
the media is present and mounted, but as
read-only access.
And there's MEDIA_REMOVED, which indicates
that the external memory is not present.
And of course, there's several other
values as well.
If your application wishes to write to
external memory,
Then it will need to request the
appropriate permission.
Specifically, you'll need to add the
WRITE_EXTERNAL_STORAGE
permission, in the application's
AndroidManifest.xml file.
Our next example application is called
DataManagement FileExternalMemory.
This application reads an image file from
the res/raw directory.
It copies that file to external storage,
it reads the image data back
from that external file, and then it
displays the image on the screen.
Let's take a look at that application
right now.
So
here's my device.
When I start the Data Management File
External Memory
application, you'll see an image displayed
on the screen.
Here it goes.
Let's
look at the source code, to better
understand where this image data came
from.
So
here's the application open in the IDE.
Now, I'll open the main activity.
In the onCreate method, the code checks
the external storage state
to ensure that the media is mounted, and
that is readable and writable.
After that, the code gets the external
file directory, where pictures are
normally stored.
And it constructs a new file object,
pointing within that directory.
Next, it checks whether a file actually
exists on the external memory.
The code then calls the copy image data to
memory method.
Let's look at that method.
Now this method starts by creating a new
output stream, that
will be used to write to a file, on the
external memory.
Next, it creates an input stream, so that
it can read image data from the res/raw
directory.
And finally, it copies the data from the
input stream to the output stream.
When this method completes, there will be
a new file in external memory.
Now, going back to the on create method,
the code gets a reference to an image
view, and insets the image URI to be
the file that was just created in external
memory.
If your application creates temporary
files, then
you may consider writing these to cache
directories.
Cache files are temporary files that may
be
deleted by the system, when storage is
low.
And these files are removed when the
application is uninstalled.
And you can get access to the Cache
directory, by using the context class's,
getCacheDir method.
This method returns the absolute path to
an
application-specific directory, that can
be used for temporary files.
Alternatively, you can also use the
context class's getExternalCacheDir
method, which returns
a file object representing a directory for
Cache files in external storage.
When your application reads and uses
larger amounts of structured and
complex data, you may want to put that
data in a database.
Android provides an implementation of
SQLite, which allows applications to
create and use in-memory relational
databases.
SQLite is designed to operate within a
very
small footprint, say less than 300
kilobites of storage.
SQLIte is however, a full fledged
relational database.
It implements most of the SQL92 standard,
and it supports highly reliable
ACID transitions, which means that it's
transactions are atomic, consistent,
isolated, and durable.
To use an SQL database in your
applications, Android
recommends that you use a helper class
called SQLiteOpenHelper.
And what you'll do, is you'll create a
subclass of this SQLiteOpenHelper class.
And in the constructor for that class,
you'll need to call the super
classes constructor, passing in some
information
about the database you want to create.
Next, you'll override the onCreate method,
the onUpgrade method as well.
Now typically, in onCreate, you'll execute
one or more
Create Table commands, which define the
database's structure and layout.
And after that, you'll use the
SQLiteOpenHelper methods,
for example, to open and return the
underlying SQLite database.
And then, you execute operations on the
underlying database.
Our last example application is called
DataManagementSQL.
This application creates an SQLite
database, and then
inserts several records, some with errors,
into the database.
The application will also display a button
labeled Fix.
And when the user presses the Fix button,
the application will
delete and update, some of those records
that were just inserted.
And it will then re-display the updated
database records on the screen.
Let's take a look at that application now.
So
here is my device.
And now, I'll start up the Data Management
SQL application.
As you can see, the application now
displays four database records,
each containing a record ID, and the name
of an artist.
At the bottom of the screen, there's also
the Fix button that I mentioned earlier.
When I press this button, record number
two, Lady Gaga, will be deleted.
And record number three, Johnny Cash, will
be
updated to correctly spell the artist's
first name.
Let me hit the Fix button now.
And as you can see, record number two has
been deleted, and
record number three now shows the correct
spelling of Johnny Cash's first name.
Let's look at the source code for this
application.
Here's the application open in the IDE.
I'll now open up the main activity.
Here in the onCreate method, we
begin by creating a new DatabaseOpenHelper
instance.
And that class is a subclass of
SQLiteOpenHelper.
Let's
take a look at that class.
The
constructor for this class, calls the
super class's constructor passing in
information, such as the name of the
database, and a version number.
Now this class's onCreate method, receives
an
SQLite database object, and then calls its
ExecSQL
method, passing in a string, which
corresponds to an actual
SQL command, that will create a table
named Artists.
And that table will contain two fields, an
integer ID, and a string for the artist's
name.
This class also has a DeleteDatabase
method, which simply deletes the database.
Now going back to the main activity, the
onCreate method continues by getting a
reference to the underlying data base,
that can be used for reading and writing.
Next, it calls the clearAll method, which
just deletes every record in the database.
After that, the code calls the
InsertArtist method,
which inserts a number of records into the
database.
Now this method first creates a
ContentValues object, and then puts
information
into that object, corresponding in this
case, to the artist's name, Frank Sinatra.
Next, it inserts the record into the
Artist table by calling the insert method.
Now since the ID field is auto generated
by
the database, the application doesn't need
to include it here.
Next, the code clears out the values
object,
and then add a second record for Lady
Gaga.
A third record for Johnny Cash, and the
fourth record, for Ludwig van Beethoven.
Now, going back up to the onCreate method,
the code calls the readArtist method,
which reads all the records in the
database, and returns a cursor object.
A cursor is essentially an iterator over a
set of records returned by a query
operation.
And this cursor is then used to create an
adapter for
the list view, that will display these
records on the display.
And finally, the code sets a listener on
the Fix button.
When the user presses this button, the
code calls the Fix method.
Let's scroll down to that method.
This method first calls the Delete method,
which finds the
record with the artist name Lady Gaga, and
then deletes it.
And after that, the method creates a
ContentValues
object, with the right spelling of the
name Johnny.
It then performs an update operation, that
first finds the record
with the misspelled name, and then
replaces it with the correct spelling.
You need to debug your database
applications, there
are several things you might need to know.
First, the database files are
stored in the data/data/package
name/databases directory.
And you examine these files, by first
opening a
shell to the emulator, or to your device,
with ADB.
For instance, if your emulator's name is
emulator-5554, then
you can issue this command to open a
shell.
And once the shell is open, you can then
use
the SQLite3 command to open the connection
to the database itself.
And from there, you can type, for example,
.help to
get more information about the specific
commands this program understands.
So that's all for our lesson on Data
Management.
Please join me next time, when we'll
discuss the ContentProvider class.
See you then.
[BLANK_AUDIO]