Hi, I'm Adam Porter, and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
Some services work independently of other
components.
They get started, they do their work, and
they quit.
Other services are instead meant to
receive
requests and to provide responses to other
components.
Sometimes those components are running in
the same application
or process as the service and sometimes,
you're not.
In these cases, components will need to
bind to the service.
That is, they need to open and maintain a
connection to the service, so they can
interact with it.
If the component and the service are
running in different processes, then there
are two common approaches for designing a
service and for binding to that service.
The first approach is to use the messenger
class.
The second is to define a remote interface
to the service using the AIDL language and
tools.
Let's talk about each of these one at a
time.
The messenger class manages a handler.
Using a messenger allows messages to be
sent
from one component to another component
across process boundaries.
Once sent, messages are then queued
and processed sequentially by the
receiving component.
So you should use this approach only
if your service can tolerate sequential
access.
Now for this approach to work, you'll have
to implement the client
components and the service so that they
can send and receive messenger messages.
On the service side, your service will
have to
create a handler for receiving and
processing specific messages.
And the service will also have to create a
messenger that provides
a binder object back to any client, that
binds to this service.
On the client side, the client binds to
the service and eventually gets back a
binder object; the client then uses this
binder object to create its own messenger.
Which essentially knows how to send
messages to
the handler that we set up inside the
service.
The client then uses that messenger to
actually send messages
to the handler, where they are then
processed by the service.
Our next example applications are called
Logging Service
with Messenger Client and Logging Service
with Messenger.
With these applications, a client sends
log messages to a
remote logging service, which is
implemented in a separate application.
A remote logging service takes these
messages and then writes them to the log.
Let's run these applications now.
So,
here's my device.
Now, I'll start the LoggingService with
messenger client application.
Again, you can see that there's a single
button, labeled Generate Log Message.
Lemme click on that now.
Let's
take a look at the log console to
make sure that the message was actually
written.
So
here's my IDE.
Let me open the log cat view.
And here you can see the log message that
was written by the log in service.
Let's look a the source code for this
application.
So here are the applications open in the
IDE.
Let's start by looking at the
ServiceLoggingWithMessenger
application and now I'll open the
LoggingService class.
As you can see, this class extends the
Service class.
And here, the code creates a
Messenger object passing in a new
IncomingMessageHandler.
The IncomingMessageHandler is defined
here.
And the handle message method receives
messages that are sent to this handler.
And in this case, if the message.what
field is log_op.
Then this code writes the message to the
log.
Lastly, this service defines an onBind
method.
This method gets the binder associated
with the mMessenger object and returns it.
And this value will eventually be passed
back to clients, that bind to this
service.
So let's switch over and
look at
the ServiceLoggingWithMessengerClient
application.
Now I'll open the LoggingServiceClient
class.
This code starts by creating an Intent
that
will be used for binding to the logging
service.
Next, the code defines an object
that implements the ServiceConnection
callback methods.
In particular, in the onServiceConnected
method, the
code creates a Messenger object passing in
the
binder that was returned from the logging
service
when this class binds to the logging
service.
This class will use this messenger to
communicate
with the login service, now scrolling down
to onCreate.
The code sets a Button listener that calls
the logMessageToService method, when this
button is clicked.
And this logMessageToService method
creates a new message object
containing a message code, and containing
the text to be written to the log.
And then it sends that message to the
logging service using the messenger
objects send method.
Continuing on, in onResume, the code calls
bindService.
Passing in the right intent, the callback
object, and
a flag that tells Android to create the
service if it doesn't already exist.
Now in onPause, the code unbinds from the
logging service.
So implementing bound services with a
messenger
as we just did is often the simplest
way to go as long as you can
tolerate having only sequential access to
the service.
When that doesn't work, though, then you
will
want to develop an AIDL interface to your
service.
AIDL stands for the Android Interface
Definition Language.
When you use this language to implement
your service, you normally do the
following things.
First, you'll define the service's remote
interface using AIDL.
Next, you'll implement the methods of that
remote interface.
After that, you'll implement the various
service life cycle and callback methods.
And finally, you'll implement the client
methods.
Let's talk about these steps.
To define the service's remote interface,
you'll need
to create an interface definition using
the AIDL language.
And this interface defines the methods
through
which components can interact with your
service.
Now as I said, this interface definition
is written in the AIDL language.
AIDL is similar in many ways to the syntax
that you use in Java when you create
interfaces.
For example, you can declare methods that
need to be implemented
if an object wants to say that it conforms
to that interface.
One way in which it differs however, is
that in AIDL, you can't declare static
fields.
Another difference is that non-primitive
parameters to methods
defined by the interface, require a
directional tag.
And this indicates how data is copied into
and out of the methods.
And the possibilities for this directional
tag are In, which
means the data is only transferred into
the remote method.
Out, which means the data is only returned
out of the remote method.
And Inout, which means the data is
transferred
both into and out of the remote method.
The parameters and return types of these
remote methods are limited to the
following types.
You can have Java primitive types such as
int, float,
and boolean, you can have a string or a
character sequence.
If you define other AIDL interfaces you
can also use those as well.
And you can use any class that implements
the parcelable interface.
You can also have lists, whose elements
are
any of those types that I just mentioned.
And these lists can be defined as generic
classes that take a type parameter.
And finally, you can also use maps, of any
of the types I've discussed.
However AIDL does not allow for generic
map types.
So here's a simple example of an AIDL
interface from the example that we'll go
over shortly.
This interface is called KeyGenerator and
it defines a single
method called getKey it takes no
parameters and returns a string.
Our next example applications
are called ServiceIDService and
ServiceIDServiceClient.
In these applications, a client in one
application
binds to a service hosted in another
application.
The client then retrieves a unique ID from
the service.
For this example, we're going to assume
that, for whatever
reason, we want the service to handle ID
requests concurrently.
And so we've decided to use AIDL to define
a remote interface to the service.
Let's see these applications in action.
So here's my device, now I'll start the
ServiceIDServiceClient application.
As you can see the application presents a
single button labeled Get New ID, when I
press this button, this application will
bind to a service to retrieve a unique ID.
This application will then display that
new ID.
So here it goes.
And there's my new ID.
Let's look at the source code for these
applications.
So here are the applications open in the
IDE.
Let's start by looking at the
ServiceIDService application.
Now I'll start by opening the
keygenerator.aidl file.
As we saw earlier this file defines the
interface
that clients can use to interact with this
service.
That is they can call one method.
GetKey and then we'll get back a string.
Now let's look at the KeyGenerator import
class.
This class implements the remote methods
defined in the AIDL KeyGenerator
interface.
First, the class defines a set of IDs that
it has already assigned.
And know that this code will not guarantee
that all keys
are unique if this service happens to be
killed and then restarted.
To do that, you would need to store and
restore the already assigned keys.
Now, in order to implement this interface,
you need to
implement the remote methods inside an
abstract inner class called Stub.
And that's just the name choice that the
AIDL
compiler makes, and you have to respect
that choice.
Here the code makes a new
KeyGenerator.Stub instance,
and then defines the getKey method in
line.
The methods of this class need to be
thread safe.
So this class first synchronizes on the
mIDs object.
And then it generates new IDs, until
it finds one that hasn't already been
assigned.
It then stores the ID, and returns a
string version of it to the client.
And finally, down in the onbind method,
the
code returns the Stub class just defined
above.
Which will be eventually given to the
client so it can interact with this
service.
Okay.
So now let's switch over and look at the
ServiceIDServiceClient application.
Now, I'll open the main activity for this
application.
In on create, the code sets up a button
that will make a call to the
KeyGeneratorService.getKey method.
It will then display the result in a text
view.
In onResume, the code binds to the
KeyGenerator service
ended onPause, the code unbinds from the
KeyGenerator service.
Scrolling down, the code creates the
service connection object.
And in particular, in the
onServiceConnected method, the code
takes the Stub that was returned from the
KeyGenerator service.
And calls the KeyGenerator.Stub
asInterface method.
This method returns an object that
essentially
represents the connection to the
KeyGenerator service.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So that brings us to the end of our
discussion on services.
And in fact, that brings us to the end of
the course.
You did it.
Congratulations.
It's been my pleasure, indeed, my honor to
be your instructor.
And I truly hope that you're leaving this
class
with much, much more than what you brought
to it.
I know I am.
Now if you remember back to the start of
the class, I asked you to
write a note to yourself, spelling out
what you hoped to learn from this course.
When you get a chance, take a look at
that note, and let us know how things
turned out.
We'd love to hear.
So that's all for now.
Maybe our paths will cross again.
I certainly hope so.
Until then, however, keep on learning.
So long.
[BLANK_AUDIO]