Hi.
I'm Adam Porter, and this is Programming
Mobile Applications for Android Handheld
Systems.
If you want to draw more complex graphics
and you want to update those graphics
frequently, then you can do your drawing
with a canvas.
Now as I said earlier, a canvas is a kind
of context or mechanism for drawing to
an underlying bitmap.
And you can access a canvas either through
a generic view object or through a special
view subclass called SurfaceView.
Usually, you'll draw through a generic
view when your updates are less frequent,
and if you take this approach, your
application should create a custom view
subclass.
And then the system
will provide the canvas to your view
through a call to its onDraw method.
If, instead, your application needs to
frequently update its
graphics, then you might consider drawing
through a SurfaceView.
With this approach, the application
creates a custom, SurfaceView subclass.
And it will also create a secondary thread
with
which drawing operations on that
SurfaceView, will be performed.
At run time, the application can then
acquire its own canvas, And
therefore, exercise more control over how
and when drawing
occurs.
This next example application is called
GraphicsCanvasBubble.
And the idea behind this application
is that it will draw a view and then
update that view.
But the updates are somewhat infrequent,
about every second or so.
So this application has an internal thread
that wakes
up once every second or so, and moves the
view.
And then uses a canvas as it redraws the
view in its new location.
Let's see that in action.
So here's my device.
And now, I'll start up the
GraphicsCanvasBubble application.
The application starts up with a bubble
drawn at a randomly selected location.
And every second or so, you can see that
the bubble is erased, moved
and then redrawn in it's new location.
Let's look at the source code
for this application.
So here's the GraphicsCanvasBubble
application open in the IDE.
Now, I'll open the main activity.
Here you can see that the application
loads a bitmap from the resources
directory.
And then it uses that bitmap to create an
instance of a custom view class called the
BubbleView.
Next, the code adds the BubbleView
instance to the layout.
And then it creates and starts a new
thread.
And that thread goes into
a loop and on each iteration, it calls the
BubbleView's move method.
Now as we'll see in a second, this method
changes the BubbleViews location.
And then, returns true or false depending
on whether the BubbleViews
new location is or is not still visible on
the display.
Next the code calls the view classes post
invalidate method.
This message tells android to redraw this
view and after that the thread
goes to sleep for a second before waking
up and starting the process one more time.
Now I'll skip over most of the details of
how the BubbleView moves itself.
And I'll focus instead on how it gets
redrawn.
So when the drawing thread calls the post
invalidate method, this
tells Android that the BubbleView thinks
it needs to be redrawn.
If so, then Android will eventually call
BubbleViews onDraw method.
Passing in the canvas, with which the
BubbleView is drawn.
Let's look at that method.
And as you can see, this method takes the
canvas passed into it and calls
its DrawBitmap method, passing in the
bitmap to draw.
Passing in the top and left coordinates of
the position at which to draw the bit map.
And finally, passing in a paint object
that defines style parameters
for this drawing operation.
Now, if we'd like to really increase the
frequency.
With which we're redrawing the bubble to
make it more smoothly glide across the
display.
Then, we might want to use a canvas and a
SurfaceView in order to do that.
And as I mentioned earlier, SurfaceViews
need a
separate, non-UI thread in which to do
their work.
So that SurfaceView operations
won't interfere with UI thread operations.
So, let's talk more about the SurfaceView
class.
A SurfaceView manages a low-level drawing
area called a Surface.
And this Surface is a dedicated drawing
area, that is positioned within the
applications view hierarchy.
To define a SurfaceView,
you need to create a custom class, which
is a subclass of SurfaceView.
And this custom class must,
must also implement the
SurfaceHolder.Callback interface.
To use this new SurfaceView, you need to
do two things.
One, you need to
setup the SurfaceView.
And two, you need to draw to the
SurfaceView that you just setup.
Let's talk about each of those steps, one
at a time.
To set up the SurfaceView, you first use
the SurfaceViews getHolder method to
acquire the SurfaceView's SurfaceHolder.
Next,
you register the SurfaceView for
SurfaceHolder callbacks.
By calling the SurfaceHolder's addCallback
method.
Now these methods are one, surfaceCreated
which is called when the SurfaceView's
surface has been created.
Until this method is called you can't draw
on the surface.
It's not ready.
Two, surfaceChanged.
This method is called whenever structural
changes,
such as changing the surface's size,
occurs.
And three, surfaceDestroyed.
And this method is called right before a
surface is destroyed.
Once this method returns, you can no
longer call operations that will draw
on the surface.
And the last setup step is to create the
thread
that will be used for executing drawing
operations on this SurfaceView.
And remember, that the SurfaceHolder
callback methods
will usually be called from the main
thread not from the SurfaceView's thread.
So you'll have to make sure that you
synchronize
access to any data that is needed by both
threads.
So once you've setup the SurfaceView you
can start drawing on it.
To draw, you'll first acquire a lock
on the canvas by calling the lockCanvas
method.
Next, you do whatever drawing operations
that you want to do on the canvas.
For example, by calling a canvas method,
such as drawBitmap.
And last, you unlock
the canvas, allowing Android to update the
display.
And you'll do this by
calling the SurfaceHolder's
unlockCanvasAndPost method.
So let's look at a different
implementation of
our last example application, called
GraphicsBubbleCanvas Surface View.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So here's my device.
And in a moment, I'll
start up
the GraphicsCanvasBubbleSurfaceView
application.
And when I do, the application will start
up and
draw the bubble at a randomly selected
location on the display.
But this time, instead of updating every
second or so, this application
will try to do as many updates as it can.
In addition,
the application will also rotate the
bubble view to give the appearance
that the bubble is twirling through space.
So here goes.
And as you can see, the bubble is smoothly
animating both moving and rotating as it
floats along.
Let's look at the source code for this
application.
So here's the
GraphicsCanvasBubbleSurfaceView
application open in the IDE.
Now I'll open the main activity.
And in onCreate, this code again loads a
bitmap from the resources directory.
And then uses that bitmap to create an
instance of a custom view class called
BubbleView.
Let's look at the BubbleView class.
The BubbleView class extends SurfaceView
and implements the SurfaceHolder.Callback
interface.
The constructive for this class does a lot
of housekeeping.
And then down at the end of the method,
there's
a call to the getHolder method, which
returns a SurfaceHolder.
The code takes that SurfaceHolder and then
registers this BubbleView
for callbacks.
Let's look at what happens when these
callbacks finally arrive.
First, we see that
when the surface for the SurfaceView is
created, this code creates
a new thread, and then starts it.
And that thread's run method
then goes into a loop.
And on each iteration of the loop,
it checks to see whether the thread's been
interrupted.
And if not, it then calls the move method,
which like before moves the bubble view
and returns a Boolean indicating whether
or not the BubbleView has left the screen.
If these checks evaluate to true, then
the code attempts to lock the
SurfaceHolder's canvas.
And if
successful, the code then calls the
drawBubble method passing in the locked
canvas.
And then finally, the application unlocks
the
canvas and allows Android to update the
display.
Let's go back for one second and look at
the drawBubble method.
Now, this method, first redraws the
canvas's background,
then it rotates the canvas and then it
redraws the bubble on the canvas.
[BLANK_AUDIO].