[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi, I'm Adam Porter, and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
If you use common applications that
display maps or web pages, then
you've probably used gestures like swiping
to scroll a view, or
inching and un-pinching your thumb and
index finger to zoom in or zoom out.
In this lesson, I'll start by discussing
MotionEvents.
Android uses this class to represent the
movement in various input devices.
Things like a mouse, a trackball, and most
common of all, your finger.
Next I'll discuss how Android takes these
motion events and delivers
them to views and other objects, so that
your application can
respond to them.
And finally, I'll finish up with
a discussion of how Android recognizes
complex
movement patterns or gestures, things like
the
pinch to zoom that I mentioned earlier.
Android uses the MotionEvent class to
represent movements in an input device.
Such as a pen, a trackball, a mouse or
your finger.
An individual movement event contains
several pieces of information.
It has an action code, which indicates the
kind of motion that has occurred.
It also contains a variety of data
associated with that motion.
For instance, it has information about the
time at which the
event occurred, which device the event
came from, the event's location.
And if appropriate, how hard the device
was pressed and more.
And as I just said, this information will
vary depending on the kind of input device
involved.
In the rest of this lesson, I'll focus
particularly on finger touch events
that are read by pressing a touch screen.
Many touch screen devices today are multi
touch devices.
That means that they can register and
track multiple touches all the same time
In Android, multi touch devices emit one
movement trace per touch source.
And each of these touch sources is
referred to
as a pointer.
When Android encounters a new pointer, it
generates a unique
ID that will remain constant for as long
as that pointer is active.
In some cases, Android will group multiple
pointers within a single motion event.
And in that case, each pointer within the
motion event can be accessed by its index.
But be aware, that that index is not
the same as the pointer's ID.
The pointer ID is constant for as long as
the pointer is active.
The index in which a pointer's data is
stored however may not be.
So let's talk about Motion Events in more
detail.
Now as I said earlier Motion Events have
an action code.
When a gesture begins,
motion events will be created, and they
will contain some of the following action
codes.
ACTION_DOWN, which indicates that a first
finger
has been, has started touching the screen.
ACTION_POINTER_DOWN, that means that we've
already had an ACTION_DOWN,
and now we have another finger that has
started touching the screen.
ACTION_POINTER_UP.
We've had an ACTION_POINTER and an
ACTION_POINTER_DOWN, and now
one of the fingers has stopped touching
the screen.
ACTION_MOVE.
Some of the fingers that are touching the
screen have changed their position.
ACTION_UP.
The last of the fingers that was touching
the screen has now stopped touching it.
And
ACTION_CANCEL.
Something has prematurely canceled the
current gesture.
While the gesture is playing out Android
will try
to ensure that it's motion events obey the
following rules.
Touches will go down one at a time.
They will move as a group.
So a single motion event can refer to
multiple pointers, and
they will come up one at a time or be
cancelled.
When you need to process motion events,
you can
use some of the following methods,
getActionMasked which returns the
action code associated with the motion
event getActionIndex,
which returns the index of the pointer
associated with this action code.
For example, if the action code is action
pointer down then you can use
this method to find the index of the
particular pointer that is just
touched down, getPointerId.
Given
an index, this method returns the stable
ID of the pointer
associated with that index.
GetPointerCount,
which returns the number of pointers
associated with the motion event.
GetX and getY, which return the
x and y coordinates of the pointer stored
at the current index.
And findPointerIndex, which returns the
index associated with a given pointer ID.
When a touch occurs on a view, Android
generates a motion event, and then
attempts to deliver that event to various
objects, one of which is the view itself.
Android delivers the motion event through
the onTouchEvent method.
This method can process the motion event,
and should end,
by returning true if the motion event has
been consumed,
and false if it is not.
Objects interested in receiving motion
events that occur
on a given view, can register to receive
those
events by implementing the views on touch
listener interface,
and by registering the object with the
view.setontouchlistener method.
The listener's onTouch method will then be
called when
an event such as pressing, releasing, or
dragging, occurs.
And this method will be called before the
touch
to view gets a chance to handle that
touch.
And again, onTouch should return true if
it consumes the motion event.
Or false if it doesn't.
In the simplest
case, you can process each touch event
independently.
But applications often need or want to
process multiple touches that are part
of a more complex gesture.
To do this, your code will
need to identify and process particular
combination
of touches for example, a double touch
will involve an ACTION_DOWN.
And then and ACTION_UP and then another
ACTION_DOWN
and finally an ACTION_UP all in quick
succession.
To give some examples, suppose you start a
gesture by placing one finger down on the
screen.
That will generate an ACTION_DOWN event.
And might assign a pointer ID of zero for
that pointer.
If you keep that finger down and move it
on the screen, you might get several
action move events associated
with pointer ID zero.
Suppose now that
you put a second finger down.
In that case you'll get an action pointer
down event, and this new pointer might get
an ID, say of one.
If you keep those fingers down and you
move them, you might get then several
action move events associated with the
pointer IDs zero and one.
And if you now lift the first finger, then
you'll
get an action pointer up event, associated
with pointer zero.
And then, if you finally lift the last
finger, you'll get an action up event
associated with pointer ID 1.
In the next example,
we'll start as before, putting down the
first finger.
Moving it, putting down a second finger,
and then moving those fingers again.
But this time, however, we'll lift the
second finger first.
In this case, we get an action pointer up
action associated with pointer ID 1.
And then finally, when we lift the last
finger, we get the action
up Action associated with the pointer ID
0.
For a last example, we'll use three
fingers.
We'll put down the first finger, then the
second, and then a third.
And then we'll move the fingers, and then
we'll lift them up.
First lifting the second finger, then the
first
finger, and then finally lifting the third
finger.
Our first example application in
this lesson is called
touchindicatetouchlocation.
And this application draws a circle
wherever the user touches the screen.
The circle's color is randomly selected,
and the application also then redraws
the circle, following the user's finger,
if it moves across the screen.
And finally, when the user
touches the screen in multiple locations.
The size of the circles that are drawn,
will
change to reflect the number of currently
active touches.
Lets take a look at this application in
action.
So here's my device.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And now I'll start up the touch indicate
touch location application.
When it starts, the screen is blank
because I'm not touching the screen right
now.
Now I'll place one finger on the screen
and that causes a
single circle to be drawn at the place
where I've touched the screen.
As I slide my finger along the screen, you
can
see that the circle is redrawn, to track
my finger movements.
Now,
I'll place a second finger on the screen.
And that causes the second circle to be
drawn under that finger.
And as you can see, the size of the two
circles, is now
about half of what you saw when there was
only a single circle.
Now, here I'll take away the second
finger, and
the first circle goes back to its original
size.
Now,
I'll put the second finger back, and again
the two circles appear at
half size.
And, I can drag these two fingers around
the screen, and the circles will follow my
movements, and finally here I'll put down
more fingers four, six, eight, ten.
I'm out of fingers now.
So now I'll move them around, and
now I'll start to take away some fingers.
Eight, six, four, two, one.
Now, let's take a look at the source code
for this application.
Here's the application open in the IDE.
Now I'll open the main activity.
This coast, this code first creates a pool
of custom views called marker views.
Marker views will be used to mark the
location of a single touch.
Next, the code defines a set that holds
the MarkerViews that are currently visible
on the display.
And now down in onCreate, the code gets
the
FrameLayout that represents the main view
of this activity.
And then it creates an OnTouchListener and
sets this as the recipient of
that listener's OnTouch callback.
Let's look at that method.
When the user touches the screen, this
listener's OnTouch method is called,
and that method begins by checking the
action code for the new motion event.
If the action code is ACTION_DOWN or
ACTION_POINTER_DOWN, then there's been a
new touch.
So the code creates and displays a new
marker view.
The code
does this by recording the pointer ID, and
pointer
index for this event.
It then takes a marker view from the
inactive list.
And it then adds that marker view to
the active set, using its pointer ID as
the key for this view.
Next, it sets the location of this marker
view, and then
it updates the total number of touches for
each currently visible marker view.
And then it adds the marker view to the
activity's main view.
Now if, instead, the action code was
ACTION_UP, or ACTION_POINTER_UP.
Then that means that a finger has been
lifted off the screen.
So the code essentially undoes
what we just finished talking about.
Now, as before, the code begins by
recording
the pointer ID and pointer index for this
event.
It then removes the marker view that was
associated with
the finger that was just lifted from the
active set.
It then adds that marker view back to the
inactive list.
And next, it updates the total number
of touches for each currently visible
marker view.
And then it removes the marker view from
the activity's main view.
And lastly, if the
action code is ACTION_MOVE.
Then the code adjusts the
location of the affected marker views, and
initiates their redrawing.
The code does this by looping over the
pointers in the motion event.
For each one, it gets the marker view for
that
pointer then it checks whether the
pointer's traveled some minimum distance.
If so, it sets a new location for that
marker view, and then calls invalidate
on the MarkerView which indicates that the
MarkerView wants to be redrawn.