[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi, I'm Adam Porter and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
Handheld devices allow users to create and
consume large amounts of rich multimedia
content.
And this content includes audio content,
like when
you listen to music or record voice notes.
Image content, like when you take and view
photos.
And video content, like when you take and
view movies.
In this lesson,
we'll talk about the multimedia classes
that Android provides, and
we'll walk through the APIs and example
applications that play
audio, that let you watch audio, let you
record audio,
and, finally, that let you use the camera
to capture images.
So, let's get started.
Android provides a number of classes and
capabilities to support the encoding and
decoding of common media formats.
Your application
can use these to play and record audio,
still images, and video.
Some of the classes we'll talk about today
will
be the AudioManager and SoundPool classes,
which allow applications to
play sound effects and audio files, and to
control a
device's audio-related hardware, such as
its speakers and wireless headset.
We'll talk about the RingtoneManager and
Ringtones.
And these are the sounds that you often
hear when a phone call
arrives, when a notification is received,
and when alarms go off.
And the MediaPlayer, which lets
applications play audio and video files.
The MediaRecorder, which allows
applications to record audio and video.
And, finally, we'll finish up by looking
at the Camera
class, which lets applications control
hard, the hardware cameras on
a device.
The first class I'll talk about is the
AudioManager.
This class manages basic audio
capabilities, like manipulating the
device's
volume, playing system sound effects, and
changing the device's ringer mode.
Applications acquire a reference to the
AudioManager
by calling Context.getSystemService,
passing in
the value Context.AUDIO_SERVICE.
And once it has a reference to the
AudioManager,
an application can load and then play
sound effects, adjust
the device's volume, and control device
hardware, for instance, by
muting the microphone, or by turning on
the Bluetooth headset.
Another related class that can be used to
play complex audio is the SoundPool class.
A SoundPool represents a collection of
audio samples or streams.
And the SoundPool allows you to mix
together
and play multiple samples at the same
time.
Let's take a look at our first example
application for this lesson.
That application is called
AudioVideoAudioManager.
And when it runs, this application
presents two buttons labeled Up and
Down that are used to increase and
decrease the device's volume.
The application also displays a button
labeled Play
that, when pressed, plays a bubble popping
sound at the current volume level.
Let's run the application now.
So, here's my device, and now I'll start
up the AudioVideoAudioManager application.
And, as promised, displays three buttons.
Up, down, and play.
The application also shows the current
volume level on a scale from zero
to ten.
Right now, the volume level is set to six.
Let me press the play button, so you can
hear the bubble popping sound.
Here goes.
[SOUND]
And now, I'll press the up button a few
times, to go to maximum volume.
And now I'll press the play button again.
>> [SOUND]
Now, I'll press the down button, and play
button
a few times, and you should hear the
bubble pop at
increasingly lower volumes.
Here goes.
[SOUND] Let's look at the source code for
this application.
Here's the AudioVideoAudioManager
application open in the IDE.
Now I'll open the Main Activity.
Here, the onCreate method gets a reference
to the AudioManager.
Next, it begins to set up its user
interface.
First, there's the text view for
displaying the current volume level.
Next, there's the up button.
And when clicked, this code plays a key
clicking sound, and
then tries to increase the volume level
and update the level display.
Next, we see the down button.
And this is almost the same as the code
for the up button.
But it decreases rather than increases the
volume level.
Next, the code gets a reference to the
play button, and then disables the button
for now.
After that, the code creates a SoundPool
object, which
it will use to play the bubble popping
sound.
The parameters for this SoundPool logic
indicate that it will have only one
audio stream, and that the stream is
played on the audio
music stream.
Next, the code loads the bubble pop sound.
Loading the sound is an
asynchronous operation, so the code sets
an onLoadComplete
listener, which will be called when the
sound is finally loaded.
And when the onLoadComplete method is
called,
the code checks whether the operation was
successful.
And if so, it enables
the play button.
Earlier the code disabled the play button,
and it did it to make sure
that it didn't try to play this sound
until the sound was properly loaded.
Next, the code sets a listener on the play
button.
When pressed, this code plays the bubble
popping sound at the current volume level.
And, after that, the code
requests audio focus, which means that it
essentially wants to
be in charge of the audio being played by
the device.
There's also some code in the onResume and
onPause methods.
The onResume method turns on the device's
speakerphone and then loads the
system's sound effects, like the key click
sound effect that we used above.
The onPause method begins by unloading the
SoundPool and releasing it's resources.
And then it turns off the device's
speakerphone, and unloads the system sound
effects.
The next classes we'll talk about are
Ringtone and the RingtoneManager.
The RingtoneManager provides access to the
audio
clips that you hear, for example, when a
phone call arrives, when you receive a new
email message, or when an alarm goes off.
And through the RingtoneManager,
applications can get and set
various ringtones, and they can play and
stop playing them.
Let's see an example application that uses
the RingtoneManager.
Now, this application is called
AudioVideoRingtoneManager.
And this application presents three
buttons,
respectively labeled Ringtone,
Notification, and Alarm.
Pressing one of these buttons causes the
associated default ringtone to play.
Let's give it a try.
So, here's my device.
Now I'll start up the
AudioVideoRingtoneManager application.
As you can see, it displays the three
buttons:
Ringtone, Notification, and Alarm.
Let me press some of these buttons.
First, let's listen to the default
ringtone as I press the ringtone button.
[SOUND] Now, let's try the default
notification ringtone.
[SOUND] And finally,
let's try the default alarm ringtone.
[SOUND] After this segment is over, try
downloading,
installing, and running this application
on your device, and then go to
your settings application and change your
default ringtones.
When you then re-run this application, you
should see
that it plays your new ringtones, not your
old ones.
So, let's look at the source code for this
application.
Here's the AudioVideoRingtoneManager
application open in the IDE.
Now, I'll open the main activity.
In the onCreate method, the code creates
three buttons.
Let's look at the ringtone button as an
example.
Now here, we see that when this button is
clicked, the code uses the RingtoneManager
to get the URI
for the default phone ringer ringtone.
Next,
the code gets the ringtone associated with
that
URI by calling the
ringtoneManager.getRingtone
method, passing in the URI.
The result of all
this is then passed into a method called
playRingtone.
Let's scroll down to that method.
Now, this method checks to see whether the
ringtone is currently playing.
And if one is, then that ringtone is
stopped by calling the ringtone class's
stop method.
A current ringtone is then set in the
mCurrentRingtone variable, and
if the current ringtone is not null then
the code will start playing it.
[BLANK_AUDIO]