[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi I'm Adam Porter and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
Android provides a class called Gesture
Detector, that
applications can use to recognize common
touch gestures.
This class can recognize gestures, such as
a confirmed single tap, a double tap.
Which is essentially two single taps in
rapid succession.
And a fling.
Which is a press, followed by a drag,
and release motion that has a reasonably
high velocity.
To use a gesture detector, your activity
will have to create an instance of the
GestureDetector class and will have to
give it an object that implements the
GestureDetector.OnGestureListener
interface.
And then the activity will need to
override it's onTouchEvent method, which
is the method that gets called when the
activity receives a touch event.
And this method will then delegate the
motion event to the gesture detectors
onTouchEvent method.
Let's look at an example application that
uses
a gesture detector to recognize a fling
gesture.
This application is called
TouchGestureViewFlipper and when it
starts,
it presents a text view that displays a
number.
If the user performs a right to left fling
gesture, then
the text view will scroll off the left
side of the screen.
And while
it does it, a new text view, displaying a
new number
will scroll in behind it, from the right.
Let's see that application in action.
So here's my device.
Now I'll start up the touch gesture, view
flipper application.
When it starts up, the screen shows a text
view displaying the number zero.
Now, if I perform a fling gesture that is
if I press and hold the view.
And then quickly swipe towards the left
side of the screen and finally lift
my finger off the screen.
Then we'll see the animation that I
mentioned earlier.
Let me do that now.
And as you can see the text view with the
number zero slid off the screen.
Going towards the left, and the new text
view, displaying
the number 1, slid into the screen from
the right.
Let
me do that a few more times.
And
notice that this gesture only works if I
swipe from right to left.
If I try it in the other direction,
nothing will happen.
Let's take a look at the source code for
this application.
So
here's the application open in the IDE.
Now, I'll open the main activity.
First of all, this application uses the
view flipper class to handle the
animations.
Now I won't go into that much here, but
feel
free to study the code, after we finish
the segment.
For now, let's focus on how this
application detects the fling gesture.
So, in on create, you can see that the
code creates a new gesture detector.
And in the constructor for this object,
the
code passes in a new simple on gesture
listener.
And this object defines an on fling
method.
When a GestureDetector detects a fling
gesture, this method will be called.
And we'll
come back to that, to this method in a few
seconds.
Right now, let's look at the OnTouch event
method for this activity.
This method gets called when a touch event
occurs.
And no view in the activity handles it.
When this method is called, it will
simply delegate the call, to the gesture
detector,
if the gesture detector eventually decides
that it has seen a complete fling gesture.
The on fling method that I just showed you
will be called.
And this on fling method receives a
parameter.
In this case, it's called velocity x, that
tells how
fast, and in which direction the swipe
gesture was performed.
In this example, if the swipe was moving
from right to left, at a speed of
more than ten pixels per second, then the
code invokes a method called switch layout
state two.
Which causes the animation of the text
views to start.
If the velocity does not meet that
criteria, for
instance, if it's a slow drag instead of a
fling,
or if it's traveling in the wrong
direction, left to right,
instead of right to left, then the fling
gesture is ignored.
To recognize more complex gestures, you
can use Android's
Gesture Builder application to create and
then save custom gestures.
This application comes bundled with the
SDK.
At runtime, you can use the gesture
libraries class to load your custom
gestures and to recognize when a user
performs one of those gestures.
To make this work, you include a
GestureOverlayView in your application.
And this view essentially intercepts user
gestures.
And then, it invokes your application code
to handle those gestures.
Here's a screenshot of the gesture builder
application.
As you can see, I've created four custom
gestures.
Next, which is a horizontal swipe, from
left to right,
no, which looks a bit like an, an X that
you make using a single stroke.
Prev, or previous, which is a horizontal
swipe from right to left, and yes,
which looks like a check mark.
On the emulator, GestureBuilder saves your
custom gestures to a file
called /mnt/sdcard/gestures.
To use these gestures you'll need to copy
this file into your applications
/res/raw directory.
Let's
look at the TouchGestures application.
This application
displays a small view with a
candidate color for the entire
applications background.
The background color for the whole
application
is initially set to gray, and the user
can use these four custom gestures that
I showed earlier to interact with this
application.
For example, if the user performs the
next gesture the background color will
cycle forward.
If the user
performs the previous gesture, the
background color cycles back.
If the user performs the yes gesture, the
application
sets the whole application's background to
the current color.
And if the user performs the no gesture,
the application's background color is
reset to gray.
Let's see the running application.
So here's my device.
Now
I'll start up the TouchGestures
application.
And when it starts up, the application's
background is generally gray.
But there's a colored square in the middle
of the screen.
If I swipe the screen from left to right.
The color of that square in the middle
changes.
And if I do it again, the color changes
again.
And I can go back to the previous color,
by swiping,
this time, from right to left, instead of
left to right.
If I decide that I like the current color,
I can perform the yes gesture.
Like so.
And as you see the whole application now
has a background of that color,
but if I change my mind I can perform the
no gesture, like so.
And as you can see, the application's
background goes back to its initial grey.
The color square reappears in the middle
of the layout and
I can keep this issuing gestures to look
at new candidate colors.
Let's
take a look at the source code for this
application.
Here's the application open in the IDE and
now I'll open the main activity.
And you notice that this activity
implements the on gesture performed
listener interface, which means that it
provides an on gesture performed method.
In on create, the code gets a reference to
the
frame layout, which it stores in a
variable called m frame.
And this is where the candidate background
colors appear.
The code also gets a reference to a
relative
layout, which it stores in a variable
called m layout.
And this is the layout for the entire
application.
Now here's the code that reads the
gestures file from the res/ raw directory.
Using the gesture libraries from raw
resource method.
This method returns a gesture library
object, and the code then
goes on to call the load method for the
gesture library.
After that, the code finds the gesture
overlay view.
Which is in the layout, and adds the
current activity as a listener
for gestures that are intercepted by the
gesture overlay view.
When the gesture overlay view detects a
gesture, it calls the onGesturePerformed
method, shown here.
And this method first calls the recognize
method, which analyzes the detected
gesture, and then scores each custom
gesture as to how much the detected
gesture resembles the custom gestures
recorded in the gesture file.
And next the code gets the highest ranked
prediction.
And then if that prediction has a high
enough score, the
code carries out the action that is
associated with that gesture.
For example, if the gesture was the yes
gesture, then the
code sets the layout's background color to
the current candidate color.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So that's all for our lesson on
multi-touch, and gestures.
Please join me next time, when we'll
discuss multimedia.
Thanks.