[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi, I'm Adam Porter, and this, is
Programming
Mobile Applications, for Android Handheld
Systems.
One of the defining characteristics of
modern hand held systems is that they can
keep us connected and networked without
tethering us to a single location.
In this lesson, we'll explore the software
and
programming practices that you'll need to
connect your applications to the network.
So I'll start this lesson by discussing
networking in general.
That discussion will focus on connecting
your applications to the internet using
the Hypertext Transfer Protocol or HTTP
specifically by using HTTP GET requests.
After that, I'll present several classes
that
Android provides to support this kind of
networking.
And lastly, I'll discuss how your
applications can process the
data they receive in response to these
HTTP GET requests.
In particular, I'll talk about two popular
data formatting languages.
One, the Javascript Object Notation
Language, or JSON.
And two, the Extensible Markup Language,
or XML.
And I'll talk about how you parse, or make
sense, of
these HTTP responses when they're
formatted in one of these languages.
So early handheld devices gave us
mobility.
You could move from one place to another,
and still perform useful computation.
However,
their networking capabilities were
primitive by today's standards.
Now moving forward, today's devices
combine powerful processors
with fast network connections over WiFi
and cellular networks.
Handheld applications will therefore often
want to make use
of these networking capabilities to access
and provide data, and
services.
Now, to help you do this, Android includes
a variety of networking support classes,
including the Socket and URL
classes, in the Java.net packages.
The HttpRequest,
and HttpResponse classes, in the
org.apache
packages.
And the URI, AndroidHttpClient,
and AudioStream classes, in the
android.net packages.
In this lesson we're going to look at
several of these
classes using each of them to implement
the same example application.
And this application interacts with an
internet service to get
information about earthquakes that have
occurred in a particular geographic
region.
And as you'll see, that data is returned
in various formats.
Now initially we'll just display the
downloaded text as is.
Later on in the lesson, I'll show you how
to
process that data to extract just the
information that you want.
Oh, and, and one other thing.
As you'll see in a second, because
this data includes geographic information,
it's really
begging to be displayed on a map, rather
than as text.
Now, we won't do that in this lesson, but
keep this in mind, because
we'll come back to this when we get to the
lesson on maps and location.
So in order to make this application work,
the code needs to create an HTTP
request, send it to a server computer,
retrieve the results,
and then display those results.
Android provides several classes for
helping with this.
Three we'll talk about now are the Socket
class, the HttpUrlConnection class and the
AndroidHttpClient.
So here's my device.
And now I'll launch the networking socket
application.
As
you can see, this application initially
displays a single button labeled
Load Data.
When I press that button, the application
will issue an HTTP GET request to an
external server.
And that server will respond with some
complex text containing the requested
earthquake data.
Okay.
So now I'll press the Load Data button and
there you can see the requested data.
Let's look at the source code to see what
it took to get that data.
Now here I've opened the application in
the IDE.
Now I'll open the main activity for this
application.
And here I'm showing the listener for the
Load Data button.
When this button is pressed, the
application will create, and then execute,
an AsyncTask called HttpGetTask.
Let's look at that class.
The HttpGetTask class first declares some
variables,
they're used in creating an HTTP GET
Request.
When the execute method is called, on
the HttpGetTask, the doInBackground method
is called.
And that method begins by creating a new
socket.
That will be connected to the host
computer, api.geonames.org
on the standard http port port 80.
Next, the code
gets the socket's output stream, and then
writes the HTTP_GET_COMMAND.
And this string will be sent to the host
computer, which interprets it
as an HTTPGetRequest, and then responds
by sending back the appropriate response
data.
And then this code continues by getting
the socket's input stream And
by passing it to a method called
readStream.
The readStream method ultimately reads the
response data from the socket's
InputStream.
And then returns the response as a
single string.
And this string is passed to the
onPostExecute method which executes on the
main thread and which
displays the response in the text view.
If we return back to the application,
you'll notice that the response text
includes not only the earthquake data, but
also the HTTP response headers.
Now normally, I wouldn't want to display
that text here.
I really just want to show you the
earthquake data.
So in the case, I should have parsed the
response and
pulled out just the data that I wanted.
In addition, you might have noticed I
didn't write any of the
error handling code that you really need
to make this application robust.
And these points, capture pretty well the
trade offs of using sockets.
The very low level, you can write whatever
you want on
the socket but in return, you have to
handle all the many
details of making the HTTP requests, all
the error
handling, and all the processing of the
HTTP responses.
The next implementation we'll look at uses
the HttpUrlConnection class.
This class provides a higher-level
interface that handles more
of the networking details than the socket
class does.
But as we'll see in a moment, it also has
a less
flexible API than our last option, the H,
the Android HTTP client class.
Now, having said that, I'll also point out
that the Android
team is not actively working on the
Android HTTP client anymore.
And it's putting it's efforts into
improving this class going forward.
So let's look at the example application
implemented this time with the
HttpURLConnection class.
So
here's my device.
And now I'll launch the NetworkingURL
application.
As before, this application initially
displays
a single button labeled Load Data.
And as before, when I press on that button
the application will issue an HTTP
GET request To an external server, and
that server will
respond, with some complex text,
containing the requested earthquake data.
Okay, so now I'll press the
Load Data button.
There you can see the requested data,
appearing in a text view.
Notice, however, that this time, the HTTP
response headers have been stripped out.
Let's look at the source code and see how
this works.
Now, here I've got the application opened
in the IDE.
Now, I'll open the main activity for this
application.
And here, I'm showing the listener for the
load data button.
As before, when this button is pressed,
the application will create and then
execute an AsyncTask called, HttpGetTask.
Let's look at that class.
When the execute method is called on HTTP
GetTask, the doInBackground
method is invoked.
That method begins by creating a new URL
object, and passing a URL string for the
desired service as a parameter.
The code then calls the open connection
method
on the URL object, which returns an
httpUrlConnection.
This object is then stored in a variable
called HttpURLConnection.
The code continues by getting the HTTP URL
connection's input stream.
And by passing it through the readStream
method.
And as before, the readStream method,
reads the response data
from the socket's input stream, and then
returns the response,
as a single string.
This time however, the HTTP URL connection
strips off the HTTP response headers and
handles the error checking for you.
Now this string is then passed to the
onPostExecute
method which displays the response in a
text view.
The third class is Android HTTP client.
This class is an implementation of the
Apache project's DefaultHttpClient and it
allows a great deal of customization.
In particular, the class breaks an HTTP
transaction into a
request object and into a response object.
So you can create subclasses
that customize the handling of requests
and their responses.
Now, by this point, you know what the
application looks like,
so let's jump straight into the code and
look at the implementation.
Now, here I've got the networking Android
HTTP client application opened in the IDE.
Now, I'll open the main activity for this
application.
And let's go right to the HTTP get task
class.
That class begins by creating a new
AndroidHttpClient object by calling the
classes newInstance method.
Now, when the doInBackground method is
called, the code creates
an HttpGet object, passing in the URL
string for that request.
Next, it creates a response handler
object.
This object is responsible for handling
the response to the HttpGet request.
In this case, a response handler is of
type basic
response handler.
Which will return the response's body.
Now we'll see a more complex response
handler, later in this lesson.
And finally, the request and the
ResponseHandler, are passed into the
execute method.
Which sends the request, gets the
response, passing it through the
ResponseHandler.
And the
result of all this is then passed on to
onPostExecute.
Which displays the response in a text
field.
[BLANK_AUDIO]