[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi I'm Adam Porter.
And this is Programming Mobile
Applications for Android Handheld Systems.
So far, our example application has
requested data
and then just displayed that data in a
TextView.
But as you saw, that data has a complex
format that's
really intended for machine processing and
not for displaying to human beings.
In fact, this is an increasingly popular
way
to transport data around the internet and
many
web services now provide data in such
formats.
In particular, two formats that we'll talk
about now are the JavaScript Object
Notation, JSON and the Extensible Markup
Language, XML.
Let's talk about each of these, one at a
time.
The first format we'll talk about is the
JavaScript Object Notation,
JSON.
This format is intended to be lightweight
and
resembles the data structures found in
traditional programming languages.
JSON data is packaged in two kinds of data
structures.
One, maps, which are essentially sets of
key and value pairs.
And two, ordered lists.
If you want more details
about JSON, please take a look at this
website.
Now, let's go back our example
application.
As you remember, that application made a
request
to a web service, for some data about
earthquakes.
Well, the response that came back was
actually formatted in JSON.
So here's that date and let's break it
apart.
First, the data comprises a JSON object
and that object
is a map and that map has one key value
pair.
The key is called earthquakes.
And the value is an
ordered list.
Now that list has several objects inside
it.
And each of those objects is itself a map.
And each of those maps again, contains key
valued pairs.
For instance, there's a key called eqid
and it's value is an earthquake ID.
There's also a key called lng and it's
value
is the longitude at which the earthquake
was centered.
And there are a bunch of other keys, as
well.
And together, all of these values provide
the data for one earthquake.
Let's take a look at an example
application that gets this data from the
internet and
then processes it to create a more human,
readable display.
So here's my device and now I'll
launch the networking Android HTTP client
JSON application.
As before, this application initially
displays
a single button labeled Load Data.
And as before, when I press that button,
the application will issue an HTTP get
request to
an external server.
And that server will respond, with some
complex text, containing the requested
earthquake data.
This time however, the data will be
summarized and presented, in a list view.
Okay, so now I'll press the Load Data
button.
And, there you can see the requested data,
summarized and presented
in a list view.
Let's look at the source code, to see how
this works.
Here I've got the application open in the
IDE.
And now, I'll open up the file that does
the downloading and displaying.
And I'm going to skip right to the HTTP
GetTask class.
Now
here, the doInBackground method is similar
to what we've seen before, but this time,
it uses the JSON response handler class to
process the response.
Let's scroll down and take a look at that
class.
The key method in this class is the handle
response method.
This method begins, by passing the raw
response through a basic
response handler which just returns the
response body without
the http response headers.
Next, the code uses
a JSON tokener to parse the JSON response
into a Java object.
And then to return that top-level object,
which in this case is a map.
Next, the code extracts the value
associated with the earthquake's key.
And in this case, that's an ordered list.
Next, the code iterates over the
earthquakes' list and for each element
of that list, it gets the data associated
with a single earthquake.
And this data is stored in Maps.
Next, the code summarizes the various
pieces of earthquake data, converting them
to a single string and adding that string
to a list, called result.
And then finally the result is returned
back to the calling method.
Now, after the doInBackground method
finishes the onPostExecute method is
called.
And it's provided the result as its
parameter.
And as you can see, this method creates
and sets a list adapter for the list
view, passing in the result list that was
computed back in handle response.
The second data format that we'll talk
about is the Extensible Markup Language,
XML.
XML is a markup language for creating XML
documents.
XML documents contain markup and content.
The markup encodes a description of
the document's storage layout and logical
structure.
The content is everything else.
And in particular,
that content comprises the response data
when
XML is used to encode an http response.
Now, if you want more details about XML,
please take a look at this website.
Now, let's go back to our example
application.
If we give a slightly different URL then
that web service will
return the earthquake data in XML format
rather than in JSON format.
So, here's that data, let's break it
apart.
First there's an element called geonames.
Nested inside that element, is a series of
earthquake elements.
And each of the earthquake elements
contains other elements that provide the
data for one earthquake.
So comparable to what we saw with the JSON
format, there's an element called eqid and
its value is an earthquake ID.
There's also the lng element, and its
value
is the longitude at which the earthquake
was centered.
And just like in the JSON example, there
are a bunch
of other elements, as well.
So if our application gets XML data from
the internet, it will need to parse
the XML document so it can create the list
view display that we saw earlier.
Android provides several different types
of XML parsers, including DOM parsers.
DOM stands for Document Object Model.
And DOM parsers read the entire
XML document and convert it into a
document model structure, a tree.
And then the application does its
processing on this tree structure.
Now this kind of parser requires more
memory, but does allow
the application to do things like
multi-pass processing of the document.
SAX parsers.
These parsers read the XML
document as a stream and as they encounter
various document entities, they
call back into the application, which can
then process the document's information.
Now, these parsers use less memory than
DOM parsers, but they're
limited to doing their processing in a
single pass of the document.
Pull parsers, like SAX parsers read the
document as a stream.
But Pull parsers
use an iterator based approach.
Where the application, rather
than the parser decides when to move the
parsing process along.
And like SAX parsers, Pull parsers also
use less memory than DOM parsers do.
But Pull parsers also give the application
greater
control over the parsing process than SAX
parsers do.
Now,
the example application looks exactly the
same as
the one we showed for parsing JSON
responses.
So, I won't show this application to you
now.
Instead, let's look at this application's
source code.
Now here I've opened the application in
the IDE.
And now, I'll open up the file that does
the downloading and displaying.
And again, I'm going to skip right to the
HTTP GetTask class.
The doInBackground method, similar to what
we have seen before, but
now it uses the XML response handler
class, to process the response.
So let's open up that class and see how it
works.
Now as before, the key method in this
class is the handle response method.
And this method begins by creating the
PullParser object.
Next, the code sets the parser's input to
be the XML
document that was returned in the body of
the http response.
And after that, the code gets the first
parser event, and then begins to iterate
over
the XML document.
Now, inside the while loop, there are
three
events that this code checks for: seeing
the
start of an XML tag, seeing the end of an
XML tag and seeing element content.
Now, when the event is a start event, The
start tag
method is called passing in the element
that is being started.
This method identifies, if this data
element
is one that needs to be saved.
And if so, it records that by setting
certain variables.
When the event is an end event, the end
tag method is called.
Passing in the element that is being ended
and again, this method identifies
whether this data element is one that's
being saved and if so, it records that.
In addition, if this is the end of the
earthquake tag, then the results string
for this piece
of earthquake data is added to the result
list.
When the event is a text event, the
text method is called, passing in the
element's content.
This method identifies which tag is
currently being
parsed and then saves the content for
later use.
And, as before,
after the doInBackground method finishes
the onPostExecute method is
called with the result passed in as the
parameter.
And that method creates and sets a list
adapter for the list
view passing in the result list that was
computed back in handle response.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So that's all for our lesson on
networking.
See you next time for a lesson on graphics
and animation.
Bye for now.
[BLANK_AUDIO]