Hi, I'm Adam Porter, and this is
Programming Mobile
Applications for Android Handheld Systems.
The example applications that we've
studied up to now have made decisions
and then taken action, now.
But what
if your application makes a decision, but
wants to take an action an hour from
now, tomorrow at midnight, or every 15
minutes from now on?
In that case, your application will need
to create and set alarms.
In this lesson, I'll start by discussing
what alarms are and how they're used.
Next, I'll discuss the Android
AlarmManager and
the APIs it provides for setting and
canceling alarms.
After that, I'll discuss the various types
of alarms that Android supports.
And finally, I'll present and discuss an
example application that uses alarms.
Now in a nutshell, alarms are a mechanism
for sending intents
at some point, or points, in the future.
And this is useful
because it allows an application to cause
some other code
to execute even when that application is
no longer running.
Once alarms have been created and
registered, they're retained
and monitored even if the device goes to
sleep.
And as we'll talk about later, depending
on how you configure
an alarm, if it goes off while the device
is sleeping, the
device can be woken up to handle the
alarm, or the
alarm can be retained until the next time
the device wakes up.
And alarms will continue to
be active until the device shuts down.
On shutdown, all registered alarms will be
canceled.
To give you some examples of alarms, the
other day, I was digging
through some Android source code and
came across several applications that use
alarms.
For instance, the MMS messaging
application uses
alarms to start a service that can
find MMS messages that haven't been
delivered
and can try again to deliver them.
The Settings application can made a device
discoverable
over Bluetooth.
And when it does this, that application
sets an alarm, and when the
alarm goes off, the application makes the
device not discoverable anymore.
And the Phone application keeps a cache of
user information.
This application uses alarms to
periodically update that cache.
If you want to use alarms
in your own applications, you do so by
interacting with the AlarmManager service.
To get a reference to this service, you
call the context classes GetSystemService,
passing in the name of the service, in
this case, Alarm_Service as a parameter.
Once you have a reference to the
AlarmManager, you can
then use some of its methods to create and
set alarms.
For instance, you can use the Set method
to set a single alarm.
And this method has three parameters.
A type, which we'll discuss shortly, a
long, representing the time at which the
alarm should go off and a PeningIntent,
which encapsulates the operation that
should occur
when the alarm finally does go off.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
You can use this method, setRepeating, to
set
an alarm that repeatedly goes off at
specific intervals.
This method has four parameters, the three
we saw in the Set method and an additional
long that specifies the amount of time
between
each successive time that the alarm goes
off.
Another AlarmManager method is
setInexactRepeating.
This method is similar to setRepeating, in
that the alarm should go off periodically,
but this method gives Android more
flexibility
in deciding exactly when to fire the
alarms.
For instance, Android might batch up
multiple
alarms of this kind and fire them at
the same time so as not to wake up the
device too many times.
And if you want to have this kind of
behavior, then your time interval must be
one of the following constants, which
specifies intervals of 15 minutes, 30
minutes, one hour, 12 hours, and 24 hours.
And if you don't use one of these
constants, then the behavior of the
alarms is the same thing that you
would have gotten had you used
setRepeating instead.
Now each of the three methods I just
showed you took a parameter called Type.
Let's talk about alarm types now.
Android provides two degrees of
configurability with respect to alarms.
One has to do with how time information is
interpreted, and the other
tells Android how to respond if the device
is sleeping when the alarm fires.
Let's look at each of these one at a time.
First, you remember that each of the alarm
setting methods took a long
as a parameter, and I said that, that long
represented a time.
Android alarms can interpret this long
value in two different ways.
One, it can consider it to be a real or
wall clock
time, and in this case, the
long represents the number of milliseconds
since
midnight January 1, 1970.
And two, it can interpret it to be a, the
system's up time, and
that is, the amount of time since the time
at which the system last booted up.
The second issue, is what should Android
do if the alarm
goes, if, when the alarm goes off, the
device is sleeping.
One possibility
is to wake up the device now, and deliver
the intent.
Another choice, is to let the device
continue sleeping, and
to deliver the intent, the next time, the
device wakes up.
So, putting all those together, there are
four possibilities, defined as follows.
RTC_WAKEUP.
Fire the alarm at the specified wall clock
time.
If the device is asleep, wake it now and
deliver the intent.
RTC.
Fire the alarm at the specified wall clock
time, but
if the device is asleep, don't wake it up
now.
Instead, deliver the intent when the
device next wakes up.
And there is ELAPSED_REALTIME and
ELAPSED_REALTIME_WAKEUP.
For these two types of alarms, Android
fires the alarm when the
device has been up for the specified time,
and if the device
is sleeping when the alarm goes off, it
will not be woken up with
ELAPSED_REALTIME.
It will be woken up with
ELAPSED_REALTIME_WAKEUP.
The last part of
the AlarmManager APIs that we'll discuss
is the PendingIntent.
As we discussed back in user
notifications, a PendingIntent holds a
regular intent and essentially serves as a
permission slip, in which one
component allows a second component to use
the underlying intent
as if it were the first component.
Three methods that can be used
to create a PendingIntent are getActivity,
which returns a
PendingIntent that can be used to start an
activity.
GetBroadcast, which returns a
PendingIntent that
can be used to broadcast an intent.
And getService, which returns a
PendingIntent that
can be used to start a service.
So now that we've learned about alarms,
let's take a look at an example
application called AlarmCreate.
This application uses alarms to gently
encourage a student to
stop playing video games and return to his
or her studies.
Let's take a look.
Here's
my device.
I'll now start up the AlarmCreate
application.
The application displays a simple user
interface with four buttons.
One button, labeled Set Single Alarm, that
sets
a single alarm to go off in two minutes.
One button, labeled Set Repeating Alarm,
that sets a repeating alarm that will
go off in two minutes, and then continue
to go off every 15 minutes after that.
One button, labeled Set Inexact Repeating
Alarm, that sets a
repeating alarm that should go off every
15 minutes starting in about two minutes.
Now because this is an inexact alarm,
Android will try to fire the alarm every
15 minutes but will exercise a lot of
flexibility in when exactly those alarms
go off.
And finally, one button labelled Cancel
Repeating Alarm, and that
will cancel any currently active repeating
or inexact repeating alarms.
Now, I'll click the button labeled Set
Single Alarm,
and as you can see, the toast message
suggests
that the application has now set a single
alarm,
and in this case, the alarm should go off
in
two minutes.
And when it does, the code will
place a user notification in the
notification area.
Let's come back at that point and see what
happens.
So, now we're back watching the device,
and there's the notification
asking if I'm playing Angry Birds again.
Let me pull down on the notification area.
The notification view tells me that this
is
a kind reminder to get back to studying.
If I click on this notification view,
the AlarmCreate application gets brought
back up.
Now before we move forward, let's take a
look at the source code for this
application.
Now here I've opened the application in
the
IDE, and now I'll open the main activity.
Let's take a look at the onCreate method.
First, the code gets a reference to the
AlarmManager service.
Next, the code creates an intent whose
target is the alarm notification receiver
class.
This intent is then wrapped in a
PendingIntent that will cause this intent
to be broadcast.
And after that, the code creates a second
intent, which this time is
targeted to another class called
AlarmLoggerReceiver.
And as before, this intent is wrapped in a
PendingIntent that
will ultimately cause the intent to be
broadcast to that receiver.
Now,
scrolling down, the code sets up the four
buttons that we saw earlier.
The first button, when pressed, will set
up two one-shot alarms.
The first alarm is scheduled to go off two
minutes after the button is pressed.
The second of this pair will go off about
five seconds later.
The second button, when pressed,
will set up a pair of repeating alarms.
The first alarm is scheduled to go off in
two minutes, or two minutes
after the button is pressed, and then go
off every 15 minutes after that.
The second alarm of the pair will go off
about five seconds after the first.
The third button, when pressed, will set
up two inexact repeating alarms.
The first alarm is scheduled to go off
roughly every
15 minutes, starting two minutes after the
button is pressed.
And again, the second alarm is scheduled
to
go off about five seconds after the first.
Now remember, because this is an inexact
repeating alarm, Android has
considerable flexibility in the exact
timing of both of those alarms.
And in particular, Android will try to
minimize the
number of times it needs to wake up the
device if it's sleeping, for instance, by
grouping separate
alarms to go off roughly at the same time.
Finally, the fourth button, when pressed,
will cancel existing alarms.
In particular, this is important for
repeating alarms, which will continue
to go off until they're cancelled or until
the device shuts down.
Returning back to the running application,
I'll now press
the Set Repeating Alarm button, and this
sets some
new repeating alarms that will first go
off in
two minutes and then every 15 minutes
after that.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's come back when we're ready.
Okay, so we're back now, and it's been
about two minutes since the alarms were
set.
There's the notification showing that the
alarm went off.
The next alarm will come along in about 15
minutes.
Let's take a break now, and when we come
back, we'll examine the LogCat output for
this application.
So a bit more than 15 minutes has
passed, and here's the application open in
the IDE.
I'll now expand the LogCat view, and I'll
filter the LogCat
output to just show log messages that have
a tag coming from this application.
I'll type tag:alarm, and that leaves just
the
messages that we're interested in now.
As you can see, there are four messages,
two from the first time the alarms
fired, and two more from when the alarms
went off again after 15 minutes.
And notice that the two alarms which were
scheduled to go off with five
seconds between them, do in fact go off
with that interval of time between them.
So those were repeating alarms.
Let's go back now to the application and
take a look at
what happens when we use the
SetInexactRepeating method to set these
same alarms.
So here's my device again.
And now I'll pull down on the notification
area
and use it to go back to the application.
First, I'll cancel the existing alarms,
and
next I'll set the inexact repeating
alarms.
So let's let the application run for
awhile, and then
we'll take another look at the LogCat
output for this application.
So here we are back in the IDE, and
about 20 minutes has passed since we last
talked.
Let's go back to the LogCat view.
And here you can see that there are now
four new messages, two from the first time
the alarms fired and two more from the
second time those alarms went off.
And some things to notice are that even
though at 11:19, we set the alarms to go
off starting in two minutes, the first set
of
alarms actually went off after four or
five minutes.
And the second thing to notice, is that
even
though the pair of alarms were scheduled
to go
off with a five second delay between them,
Android
has actually fired them at essentially the
same time.
And again, because these are inexact
repeating alarms,
Android was free to modify the exact alarm
timings.
So that's all for our lesson on alarms.
Please join me next time for a discussion
of networking.
See you then.
[BLANK_AUDIO]