[BLANK_AUDIO]
HI, I'm Adam Porter and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
The next threading support class that
we'll discuss is the AsyncTask class.
This class provides a general framework
for
managing tasks, that, as in our previous
examples,
involve work that has to be shared between
a background thread and the UI thread.
The general work flow that you follow when
you're using an Async task,
is that work is divided between a
background thread and the UI thread.
The background thread performs the long
running
operation, and can optionally report its
progress.
The UI Thread on the other hand, is
responsible
for the initial setup of the long running
operation.
It's responsible for publishing
intermediate progress information,
should the background thread report any,
and it's responsible for
completing the operation after the
background thread has done its work.
AsyncTask is a generic class.
It takes three type of parameters, Params,
Progress, and Result.
Params is the type of the parameters that
are input to the As-, to the AsyncTask.
Progress is the type of any intermediate
progress reports, and result is
the type of the result that is computed by
the Async task.
The workflow of an Async task goes as
follows, first, the onPreExecute method
is run in the UI thread before the
doInBackground method starts.
OnPreExecute will usually set up the long
running operation.
After that, the doInBackground method does
the
bulk of the operation in the background
thread.
And this method takes a variable list of
input
parameters and it returns a result of type
result.
Now, while doInBackground is running, it
can optionally call
the publishProgress method, passing in a
variable list of values which
presumably provide some indication of the
long running operations progress.
If the background thread makes calls to
publishProgress, then some calls to
onProgressUpdate would normally
be made in the UI thread, as long as the
background thread is still running.
And finally, onPostExecute will be called
in the UI thread
with the result, with the result returned
by the background thread as its parameter.
Let's look at a version of our
icon loading application implemented with
an Async task.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Here I'll start up the thread Async task
application.
It looks similar to the previous examples,
but I've added a new UI element,
a progress bar that represents how much of
the bitmap loading has been done already.
So, here I'll press the Load Icon button,
and you
can see that a small progress bar has
appeared and
it's slowly getting filled in.
I'll now press the Other Button and we see
the familiar text pop up, and finally,
there's the bitmap.
Let's look at the source code for this
application.
Here I will start up the threadAsycTask
Now I'll open the main activity file.
And here I'm displaying the button
listener for the load icon button.
This code creates a new instance of the
load icon task.
And
then calls execute on it, passing in the
icon's resource ID as a parameter.
So let's look at the LoadIconTask class in
more detail.
LoadIconTask is an Async task and its type
parameters
are integer for params, integer for
progress, and bitmap for the result.
The first method we'll look at is
onPreExecute.
This method is executed in the UI thread,
and it's
purpose is to make a progress bar visible
on the display.
The next method is doInBackground.
This method receives an integer as a
parameter.
This integer is the
resource ID for the bitmap that was passed
in to the load icon task's execute method.
DoInBbackground does the work of loading
the bitmap.
As it does this, it periodically calls
publishProgress, passing in an
integer which represents the percentage of
the loading that's been done so far.
And again, this example's a bit contrived
in the hope of keeping things simple.
The example might have been a bit more
realistic though,
if we were downloading an image from the
internet, or if we were waiting for the
result
from a database query, but hopefully this
still gives
you a good flavor of how Async tasks work.
The next method is onProgressUpdate.
This method runs in the UI thread,
receives the integer that was passed into
publishProgress, and then sets the
progress bar
to reflect the percentage of work done.
And finally, the last method is
onPostExecute.
This method, again, runs in the
UI thread, and it receives the just loaded
bitmap as a parameter.
It first makes the progress bar invisible,
since that's no longer
needed, and then it sets the loaded bitmap
on the image view.
The last thing I want to talk about in
this lesson is the Handler class.
Like the Async task, the Handler class is
designed to support handing off work
between two threads.
The Handler class is more flexible,
however, in that it will work for
any two threads, not just for a background
thread and the UI thread.
A Handler is associated with a
specific thread.
One thread can hand off work to another
thread by sending messages
or by posting Runnables to a Handler
that's associated with that other thread.
So first, let's discuss messages and
runnables, and then
we'll get into the architecture of the
Handler class itself.
Now, you already know about runnables.
You use these when the sender knows
exactly what work steps it
wants performed, but it wants that work
performed on the Handler's thread.
A message, on the other hand, is a class
that can contain data
such as a message code, an arbitrary data
object, and some integer values.
And you use
messages when the sender thread wants to
indicate an operation that should be done
in another thread, but it leaves the
implementation of that operation to the
Handler itself.
So, now let's talk about how Handlers use
these messages and runnables.
Each Android thread is associated with a
MessageQueue and a Looper.
The MessageQueue is a data structure.
It holds messages and runnables.
The Looper takes these messages and
runnables off
of the MessageQueue and dispatches them as
appropriate.
Now this graphic depicts a thread a, that
has created a runnable.
And that has used a Handler object to post
that runnable to the Handler's thread.
When thread A does this, a runnable is
placed
on the MessageQueue of the thread
associated with the Handler.
Now something pretty similar happens with
messages.
And this graphic depicts a thread B that
has created a message, and that is
used a Handler's, a handler's sendMessage
method
to send that message to the Handler's
thread.
When thread B does this, the message is
placed on the MessageQueue associated with
that Handler.
Now, while all this is going on, the
Looper object is
sitting there, just waiting for work to
appear on the MessageQueue.
And when that work does appear, the Looper
reacts in one of
two ways, depending on the kind of work
that has just arrived.
Now, If that work is a message, the Looper
will handle the message by
calling the Handler's handleMessage
method, and passing in
the message itself.
If instead, that work is a runnable,
then the Looper will handle it by simply
calling, that runnable's, run method.
Now, here are some of the methods that you
use when
posting runnables to a Handler.
We've already seen the post method, there
are a number of other
methods that allow you to schedule work
for execution at different times.
For instance, you can use the postAtTime
method to add a
runnable to the MessageQueue, but to run
it at a specific time.
There is also a postDelayed method, and
that allows you to add a runnable to the
MessageQueue, but to
run it after a specified delay.
If you
want to send messages, you first need to
create the message.
One way to do that is to use the Handler's
ObtainMessage method, which gives you
a message with the Handler already set.
You can also use the message
class's obtain method.
And once you have the message, you'll want
to set the data for the message.
There are a number of variations for
doing this so please check out the
documentation.
As with runnables, there are a number of
methods that you can use to send the
message.
There is the sendMessage method that we
just talked about.
There's also a version that allows you to
put the message at
the front of the MessageQueue to have it
execute as soon as possible.
There's a sendMessageAtTime method to
queue
the message according to the specified
time.
There's also
a sendMessageDelayed method that queues
the message at the current time
plus the specified delay.
Let's look at the source code
for versions of our running example that
were implemented using Handlers.
Here's the ThreadingHandlerRunnable
application.
I'll now open up this application's main
activity.
And first, you see that this code is
creating a new Handler.
This Handler will be created by the main
UI thread.
So the runnables that this Handler
receives
will be executed in the UI thread.
Now, here I'm showing you the button
listener for the load icon button.
When the user presses the load icon
button,
this code creates and starts a new thread,
whose
run method is defined by the runnable load
icon task.
Let's look at that class.
Now this run method begins by posting a
new
runnable that when executed, will make the
progress bar visible.
It continues by loading the bitmap.
And while it's doing that,
it periodically publishes its progress by
posting another
runnable that calls setProgress on the
progress bar.
It then posts a runnable that sets the
newly loaded bitmap on the display.
And it finishes by posting a last
runnable, then makes the progress bar
invisible.
Let's also look at a second version of
this application that send messages,
instead of posting runnables.
Here's the ThreadingHandlerMessages
application.
I'll now open up this application's main
activity.
And first, you see that this code is
creating a new Handler.
And again, this Handler will be created by
the main UI thread.
The work that this Handler performs will
be executed in the UI thread.
As you can see,
this Handler has a handleMessage method,
in
which it implements the various kinds of
work.
This method starts by checking the message
code that's in the message.
And then, it takes the appropriate action
for that message code.
For instance, if the code is
set_progress_bar_visibility,
then this code sets the visibility status
of the progress
bar.
If the code is instead progress_update,
then this code sets the progress state on
the progress bar.
If the code is set_bitmap, then the code
sets the bitmap on the display.
Now, let's go to the button listener for
the load icon button.
Same as before, when the user presses the
load icon button, this
code creates and starts a new thread whose
run method is
defined by the runnable loadIcon task.
And this run
method begins by obtaining a message with
the code set to
set_progress_bar_visibility, and
with an argument indicating that the
progress bar should be made visible.
It then sends that message to the Handler,
which will handle it, and
make the progress bar visible.
It then continues by loading the bitmap.
And while it's doing that, it periodically
publishes progress by obtaining and
sending a message with the code
progress_update, and with an argument that
indicates the percent, the percentage of
work done.
This will result in the Handler calling
setProgress on the progress bar.
It then obtains and sends a message to set
the newly loaded bitmap on the display.
And finally, it sends a last message to
make the progress bar invisible.
So that's all for this lesson on threads,
Async tasks, and Handlers.
Please join me next time when we'll talk
about alarms.
Thank you.
[BLANK_AUDIO]