Hi.
I'm Adam Porter.
And this is Programming Mobile
Applications For Android Handheld Systems.
Locations indicate real places around us.
And so it often makes sense to visualize
locations using maps, which are visual
representations of area.
Android provides mapping support through
the Google Maps Android
v2 API.
This API provides several different kinds
of maps, specifically normal maps, which
look like traditional road maps.
Satellite maps, which display aerial
photographs of an area.
Hybrids maps, which combine satellite
photographs and road maps.
And terrain maps, which display
topographic
details such as elevation.
Android allows your application to
customize maps in several ways.
For instance, you can change the area of
the map that's visible to the user.
You can add icons, called markers, at
specific places on the map.
And you can add overlay images on top of
the map.
You can make the map respond to gestures,
such
as a two finger stretch and pinch to zoom.
And a two finger rotation to rotate the
map.
And you can also have the map indicated
the user's current location.
For instance by placing a special marker
on the map.
To display maps, your application will
probably use some of the following
classes.
Google map,
which represents and manages the map
itself.
Map Fragment, which displays a Google map,
within a fragment.
Camera, which defines the part of the map
that's visible on the screen.
And defines the viewpoint from which the
user is seeing the map.
And marker, which represents icons,
sometimes
with popup windows, that indicate
locations
on the map.
And then allow your application to
display information associated with those
locations.
To set up and run a maps application,
you'll need to take some extra steps.
For instance, you'll need to configure the
Google Play services SDK.
You'll need to obtain an API key that
identifies your application.
You'll need to specify
permissions, settings, and the API key in
the Android manifest dot XML file.
And then you'll need to add the map to
your application.
And these steps are described in more
detail.
At the following url.
In order to use the maps, you'll need to
include several permissions.
You'll need the internet permission, so
that map
images can be downloaded from Google Map
servers.
You'll also need the access_network_state
permission.
Which the maps API uses to determine
whether it can download data.
You'll need the write_external_storage
permission because map data needs to be
written to the device's external storage
area.
And you'll need the
google.android.providers.gsf
Dot permission, dot read services
permission,
and that's so the maps API can access
Google Web Services.
And, if your map means to require location
information, for
instance, to display the user's current
location then you'll also
need to specify Either one or more of the
access underscore course
location and access underscore find
underscore location permissions.
Our next example application is called
map, earthquake, map.
And this application acquires earthquake
data from a server.
And then displays that data on a map,
using clickable markers.
Let's take a look.
So
here's my device.
And before I show you the map earthquake
map application,
let me take you back to the lesson on
networking.
If you remember, in that lesson.
I showed you the networking Android
HTTP client JSON application, which
issued a network request for earthquake
data from the
api.geonames.org web service.
And that request returned a list of
earthquakes that had occurred in a
particular
geographic region, and then the
application displayed
that data in a simple list view.
I'll now start that application so you
can remember what its user interface
looked like.
Here it goes.
As you can see, the application gets the
earthquake
data, and then presents it in a list view.
Now this is certainly fine.
The data I wanted is there on the screen.
But the user interface isn't all that
helpful to me.
For example, I can't really visualize
where
on the Earth these locations really are.
And I can't easily distinguish
major earthquakes from lesser strength
earthquakes from lesser strength
earthquakes.
So let's now look at the map, earthquake,
map, application.
And we'll see the same data but this time
it's presented in a map.
Here goes,
as you can see, instead of a list view
showing lots of text the
earthquake data now appears as a set of
markers on a map of the world.
The location of the marker tells us where
the earthquake occurred.
And the color of the marker indicates the
magnitude of the earthquake.
Markers that are more red in tone indicate
higher magnitude earthquakes.
Markers that are more blue in tone
indicate lower magnitude earthquakes.
And in addition, if I touch a marker, a
pop-up window will appear showing the
magnitude of that earthquake.
Now let me zoom in and touch a few
markers.
Okay, let's take a look at the source code
for this application.
Here's the application opened in the IDE.
Now I'll open the main activity.
In On Create, the application sets the
content view to the main.xml
file in the res/layout directory.
Lets open that file now.
And here you can see that the entire
layout is comprised
of a single fragment that is provided by
the
com.google.android.gms.maps.mapfragment
class.
By turning back to the main activity, the
application creates and starts an axync
task, which acquires the earthquake data
in the do in background method.
And then it parses it and updates the map
In the onPostExecute method.
So let's scroll down to the onPostExecute
method.
This method begins by getting a reference
to the Google Map underline the
MapFragment.
Next, it iterates through the result data.
And for each EarthQuakeRec in that result
data.
This code add a new marker.
And each marker is created by creating a
marker options object
and then passing that object to the Google
maps ad marker method.
And as we've seen with other API's
the marker options class uses a fluent
interface.
And so the code first creates a new empty
marker option object, and then sets the
marker's position, by calling
the position method, and then it tacks on
the text that
will appear in a pop up information window
when the user touches the marker.
By calling the title method.
In this case the title simply displays the
earthquakes magnitude.
And after that the
code sets the color of the marker by
tacking on a call to the icon method.
Passing in the default marker, but setting
it's color to reflect the earthquake's
magnitude.
Finally the code calls the mass moveCamera
method
to center the map at a particular
location.
Now to keep this example simple, I
precomputed
the map center.
But of course it would be much better and
more robust to
compute the center based on the actual
data returned by the webservice.
So that's all for our lesson on location
and maps.
Please join me next time when we'll
discuss data management.
See you then.