[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi, I'm Adam Porter, and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
A few years ago my family spent some time
in Montreal, Canada
and right as we arrived it began to snow
and snow and snow.
And of course we, quickly found out that
my
two daughters had forgotten to pack their
snow boots.
So, we needed to buy boots and we needed
to
buy them from a store that was close to
us.
So I whipped out my mobile phone.
And I ran a search for boots in the local
area.
The application came back with a list of
shoe stores plotted on a map.
The application also allowed me to get
directions from my current location to the
stores.
We followed those directions, bought some
boots and saved our vacation.
Now I'm sure many of you could recount
similar experiences.
Sometimes the information we need depends
critically on where
we are at the time we need that
information.
To help out in these situations, Android
includes support for location and maps.
In today's lesson,
I'll talk about some of the support.
I'll talk about what location information
is, and I'll go over
the classes that your applications will
use to get that information.
I talk about maps, which allow you to take
location information and display it
visually to your users.
And I'll finish up by going over the
classes that Android provides,
to let you display and customize map.
So generally speaking, mobile applications
can benefit from being location aware.
That is no where bay, and other things
are,
at a partic, at a particular moment in
time.
And so Android allows applications
to determine and manipulate location
information.
Now earlier I gave an example
of using location capabilities, to find
stores near my current location.
And then to get directions from my current
location to one of those stores.
In addition, applications can also use
this capability to
do things like define a geographical area
or geofence.
And then to initiate actions when the user
enters.
Or exits the Geofence.
Android provides several support classes
to make all of this possible.
One of our classes is the location class.
A location represents a position on the
Earth.
A location instance contains information
such as
latitude, longitude, a time stamp and
optionally
an estimated accuracy, altitude, speed and
bearing.
Location information comes from location
providers and
devices can have access to multiple
location providers.
Now the actual data may come from sources
such
as GPS satellites, cell phone towers and
WiFi access points.
Specifically, applications can request
information from the network
provider, the GPS provider and passive
provider.
Let's look at each of these, one at a
time.
The network provider, determines location
based on cell tower and
WiFi access points.
If you want to use this provider,
then you must declare either the
ACCESS_COARSE_LOCATION
permission.
Or the ACCESS_FINE_LOCATION
GPS provider gets its location permission
from GPS satellites.
To use this provider, you must declare the
ACCESS_FINE_LOCATION permission.
The passive provider doesn't actually turn
on any devices.
It just returns locations that happen to
have
been calculated through the requests of
other applications.
So using this provider requires
that you declare the ACCESS_FINE_LOCATION
permission.
Now while you can get location information
from each of these different sources,
each one offers a different set of trade
offs with respect to cost.
Accuracy, availability, and timeliness of
the data it provides.
Let's look at some of the providers,
available in Android.
The GPS provider relies on communicating
with a satellite.
And so, this provider is generally the
most expensive but gives the most accurate
readings.
It also takes the longest amount of time
to provide that very accurate reading, and
the
user needs to have a clear view of
the sky when they're communicating with
the GPS satellite.
The network provider is cheaper than the
GPS provider.
But, it may give less accurate readings.
It takes less time to return location
information, but it's only useful
when you're in the range of a cell tower
or WiFi access point.
The passive provider is the cheapest to
use.
You're essentially just reusing
measurements that already have been taken.
So it's fast,
but it may turn out that there are no
recent readings when your application asks
for that information.
One way to access location information is
to use the location manager class.
The location manager is a system service
for accessing location data.
You acquire a reference to the location
manager by calling the context
classes get system service method, passing
in an ID for the service.
Context.LOCATION_SERVICE.
Once you have a reference
to the location manager, you can use it to
get and use location information.
For instance, you can determine the last
reading taken by a particular provider.
You can register for location updates to
find out when new location information is
acquired.
And you can also register to receive
intents.
When the device nears or moves away from a
given geographic region.
If you want to be informed when new
locations
are determined, you can implement and use
a location listener.
The location listener interface defines
the callback
methods that are called when location
changes.
Or, when the status of
a location provider changes.
A location listener interface includes the
following methods.
On location changed.
Which gets called when a new location was
determined.
onProviderDisabled and onProviderEnabled,
which are called when
the user disables or enables a particular
provider.
And onStatusChanged,
which is called when a provider's status
changes.
If your application can't get a recent
reading from the
system, it will then need to acquire its
own reading.
And to do this, your application will
normally perform the following steps.
First, it will start listening for updates
from location providers by registering a
location listener.
Next, it should maintain and update a
current best estimate,
as it begins to receive location updates.
And as this process unfolds,
the application should determine when the
current best estimate is good enough.
And at that point it should stop listening
for location updates by unregistering the
location listener.
And finally, it can use that best estimate
as the current location.
Now when you're determining whether your
location is good
enough, there are several factors that you
might want to consider.
For example, for how long should you keep
measuring?
For instance, a navigation system might
need continuous measurement.
While a restaurant finder application
might just need a single measurement.
Another question is, how accurate
a measurement do you actually need?
And again, a navigation system needs to
know
your location to say, within ten meters or
so.
A restaurant application, might just need
to know what city you're in.
And in that case, you'd only need to know,
you're
location to say, within a kilometer, or
maybe even less.
And of course, the choices you make here,
clearly impact,
battery usage.
The example application is called,
location, get location.
This application, first acquires and
displays, a, the last known location, from
all the providers on the device.
If these readings are too old, or have too
low accuracy.
Then the application acquires and displays
new readings
from all the providers on the device.
Let's give the application a run.
So here's my device.
Now, I'll start the location GetLocation
application.
When the application starts up, it
displays
the best previous location estimate from
the device.
This information is then displayed using
red text.
Since this reading is either not recent
enough
or doesn't have enough accuracy, the
application goes on
to acquire new location estimates, and you
can see
that these new readings are displayed
using grey text.
Let's look at the source code for this
application.
So here's the application open in the IDE,
now I'll open up the main activity.
And let's scroll down to the on create
method.
And here we see that the code acquires a
reference to the location manager.
Next, it calls a method called best last
known location.
This method
will find the last known location from
every location provider, and then
will return the most accurate of
these measurements that also meets certain
criteria.
If no readings meets those criteria, and
the method returns null.
Next, the code displays information about
the last reading.
After this, the code
continues by defining a location listener.
And in the listener's on location change
method, the code determines
whether the new location is better than
the current best estimate.
If so, the code then updates the best
estimate, and then updates the display.
Now, if the accuracy is less than
min_accuracy,
then the current location is considered
good enough.
And so the code unregisters the location
listener.
Now, scrolling down, you see the on resume
method.
This method checks to see whether the
current best estimate, is
of low accuracy, or was taken more than
two minutes ago.
If so, the code registers listeners for
both
the network provider, and for the GPS
provider.
After that, the code schedules a runnable,
that will unregister the listeners after
a fixed period of time.
The code will also unregister the location
listener, if the activity's onPause method
is called.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Here are some tips you can use to
save battery power when you're creating
location aware applications.
First, always check the last known
measurement.
If that's good enough, then there's no
need to take new measurements.
Return updates as infrequently as possible
and limit the total measurement time.
Some applications, such as an application
that tracks a jogger.
Need to update more frequently and need to
keep measuring
while the application is running because
the user's location is changing.
Applications like the one we just saw
though will need a
single good measurement so they can
measure infrequently and for less time.
Use the least accurate measurement
necessary, and
only use GPS if you really need too.
Turn off the updates in OnPause.
[BLANK_AUDIO]