Hi, I'm Adam Porter and this is
Programming Mobile Applications, for
Android Handheld Systems.
So let's take a deeper look, at these life
cycle methods.
The first method that gets called, is
onCreate.
onCreate gets called, when the activity is
first created.
Now typically, onCreate is used to
initialize the activity, and will
carry out the following four functions.
It will call super.onCreate, so Android
can do some of its own initialization.
It will set the activity's content view,
which
tells Android, what the activity's user
interface should be.
Next, it will capture and retain any
references it needs,
to the various views or elements of the
user interface.
And finally, it will configure the user
interface
views and elements, as required.
So, let's take a look at map locations
onCreate method.
Here, I've opened up the map location
application
in Eclipse, and now I'll open up the map
location activity, and here, as you can
see,
the map location class, is a subclass of
activity.
And it overrides activity.onCreate.
Inside the onCreate method, you see the
four functions, we just talked about.
First, there's a call to super.onCreate.
Next, there's a call to set content view,
passing in the ID of a layout
file, as a parameter.
After that, the activity stores references
to an edit text view and to a button,
which appear in the user interface.
And finally, onCreate attaches a listener
to the button.
Android calls this listener code, every
time the user presses
this button.
So, this listener code is listening, for
presses of the button.
OnRestart is another life cycle method.
It gets called, if the activity that has
been stopped, but is about to be started
again.
And you can use onRestart to handle, any
special processing that you need that, or
that is needed only after the activity's
been stopped, but is about to start again.
onStart is called, when the activity is
about to become visible.
And some typical applications for this
method include,
starting when visible-only behaviors, like
requesting location sensor
updates or loading or resetting persistent
application state.
Things like, updating the unwritten
messages
queue, for an email reader application.
The onResume method gets called, when the
activity is
visible and about to start interacting
with the user.
And some things you do in this method, are
to start foreground only behaviors.
Things like starting animations, or
playing a background soundtrack.
onPause is called, when your activity's
about to lose focus.
In this method, you can shut down
foreground only behaviors, things like
killing animations.
And you should also save any persistent
state, that the user has edited.
onStop is called, when the activity is no
longer visible to the user.
At this point, it's possible, that the
activity may be started later.
So some typical things to do here, include
caching activity state, that
you'll want to restore, when the activity
is later restarting, an onStart is called.
And remember, onStop is not always called,
when an activity terminates.
For instance, it may not be called, if
Android kills the application's process,
due to low memory.
So, don't wait to save persistent data in
this method, go do that back in onPause.
onDestroy is called, when the activity is
about to be destroyed.
And some typical actions to do here,
include releasing activity resources.
For example, shutting down private
threads,
that were started by this activity.
And again remember, onDestroy may not be
called at all.
For example, when Android kills an
application,
due to low memory on the device.
So, we're turning back to map location.
You'll see that I've also
overridden, most of the activity life
cycle methods, including
onStart, onRestart, onResume, onPause,
onStop, and onDestroy.
In each of these methods, you'll see that
I've
placed a method call, that logs some
information about
the method being called.
And I encourage you to run the map
location application yourself, and
to watch the log cat view, to see exactly
what's being written.
And I want you to try pressing different
buttons,
like the back-button and the home button,
and different
keys, to verify for yourself, that the
life-cycle method
calls, are following the graphic depiction
that we saw earlier.
So now that we've seen the activity
life-cycle in action, let's
take a look, at how one activity can
programmatically, start another activity.
To start an activity programmatically, you
first create an
intent object, that specifies the
activity, that you want to start.
And then, you pass this newly created
intent to
methods such as start activity, or start
activity, for result.
Start activity will start up the desired
activity,
pushing the current activity out of the
foreground.
Start activity for result, will also start
up the desired activity, but it will do so
with the expectation, that the start of
activity
will provide a result back to that calling
activity.
And in this case, the result is
communicated
back, by a call to that activity's
onActivity
result method.
And we'll come back to that in a few
minutes.
So, for now, let's go back into Eclipse,
and look
at how map location actually starts up the
Google Maps activity.
Here I'm showing where map location has
attached a listener, to the show map
button.
Whenever the user clicks this button, the
listener's onClick method, will be called.
And as you can see, that code creates an
intent called
geo intent, and then passes geo intent to
the start activity method.
And the end result of this is that, a
Google Maps activity will open up,
showing a map, centered on the address,
that the user entered.
Now you remember, that entering an address
in Map Location was pretty slow.
Well, here I'm going to show you a
different application, that instead of
asking the user to enter an address
through the keyboard, we'll allow him
or her to select a contact from the
contacts application, and allow
him or her to use the address of that
contact, as the address
to center the map on.
Let's take a look at this application,
called MapLocation from Contacts.
So,
here's my device running.
I'll launch the MapLocation from Contacts
application.
And now you see a button, that will allow
me to select an address from an existing
contact.
When I click on that button, a new
activity is started.
Now this activity is actually part of the
contacts application, which will
show me my contacts, and allow me to
select one of them.
So here, I'll do that and I'll select my
own name, Adam Porter.
Now, the context application had no idea,
what
I want to do with this selected contact.
In particular, it can't start or show the
map itself, based on this contact.
It just wasn't designed to do that.
So what I've actually got happening here,
is that
map location from contacts, has asked the
context application
to return the data to it, once the user
selects the contact.
And it does that by starting the contacts
application via
start activity for result, rather than, by
using start activity.
Now once the contact is selected,
MapLocation from contacts will then
receive
the selected data, and it will call Google
Maps, to display that information.
So, let's see that in the code.
Now here, I'm opening the map location
from contacts application, in Eclipse.
And the structure of the main activity, is
pretty similar to what we saw in map
location.
But you'll notice that the code in
the button listener, is a little bit
different.
In particular, this code creates a
slightly different intent, and then
passes that intent as a parameter, to
start activity for result.
We'll look at intent in more detail in the
next lesson, but you can also
see here, that start activity for result
takes
a second parameter, which represents a
request code.
And this will come in handy later, when
the result is returned back to the started
activity.
Once the new activity is started, it is
responsible for setting
the result, that should be returned back
to the calling activity.
And it does this, by calling
Activity.SetResult, passing in
a result code, and optionally, patching in
some result data.
Now, these result codes include some
built-in codes such as result canceled,
which indicates that the user chose not to
complete the activity, normally.
They probably hit the back button, for
example.
And result OK, indicating that the
activity in fact, completed normally.
Developers can also add custom result
codes, after
the the built-in result code, Result First
User.
Now before the activity ends, the activity
must set its result, by calling
set result, and this result will
eventually
be transmitted back to the calling
activity
via the call to, on activity Result.
So, let's take a look at that code in the
map location, from contacts application.
Here's, on activity result.
As you can see, its parameters include the
initial request
code, that was passed in to start activity
for result.
The result code used by the started
activity, when it called set result.
And an intent
object, if it was passed in, when Set
Result was called.
On Activity Result usually starts off, by
checking the result code
and request codes, to determine what to
do, with that particular result.
In this example, the next steps are to
retrieve the underlying contact data,
and to parse it to extract, just the
postal address of the contact.
Now, the details aren't important now, so
I'll skip
over them.
But once the postal address has been
extracted, map
location from context, operates just like
map location did.
It processes the data, so that it's in a
format that Google maps expects, puts that
data into an intent object, and then calls
start activity, passing in that intent.
The last topic I'll discuss today, is
handling configuration changes.
A device's configuration, refers to device
and application characteristics, related
to application resources.
Things like languages used, screen
size, keyboard availability and device
orientation.
Now, these characteristics can change at
run time and
when they do, Android will usually kill
the current
activity and then restart it, with
the appropriate resources, for the changed
configuration.
Now since configuration changes can happen
frequently while using an application,
you want to make sure, that your life
cycle method code, is fast.
Consider a device orientation changes, for
example.
If you move the device, from portrait mode
to landscape mode and
back to portrait mode, that will cause the
current activity to be
killed and restarted, twice.
So, if your start-up code is slow, that's
really
going to affect your user's experience
with the your application.
So, to improve the speed of configuration
changes, if
you need it, Android allows you to do two
things.
One, as the change is occurring, you can
create and
save an arbitrary Java object,
that essentially caches important state
information.
And two,
you can manually handle the configuration
change,
avoiding the whole shutdown and restart
sequence, altogether.
Let's talk about each one of those, one at
a time.
So, to speed up reconfiguration, I said
you can cache
hard to recompute data and store it in a
Java object.
And one way to do this, is by overriding
the onRetainNonConfigurationInstance
method, which
would be called sometime between,
onStop and onDestroy.
And the object that you build and return,
in onRetainNonConfiguration instance
can be retrieved, when the activity
is recreated by calling
getLastNonConfiguration instance.
And that's usually done during the call to
the activity's onCreate method, when you
recreate the activity.
Now, note that these methods have been
deprecated
in favor of other methods in the fragment
class, and we haven't discussed fragments
yet, but we'll come
back to it in a later lesson, when we do.
And the second thing you can do to speed
up reconfiguration, is
to avoid the whole kill and
restart sequence altogether, for specific
configuration changes.
And to do this, you declare those specific
changes
that the, your activity will handle, in
the androidmanifest.xml file.
For example,
this xml snippet indicates, that my
activity will manually handle
changes in device orientation and screen
size, and keyboard accessibility.
So, if you do handle come configuration
changes
manually, then when those configuration
changes occur at
run-time, your activity will receive a
call to
onConfigurationChanged, and as a
parameter, this method will
receive a configuration object, which
details the new configuration.
So, your code can then read this object,
and make whatever changes it needs to.
So, that's all for today's discussion of
the activity class.
Please join me next time, when we'll
discuss the intent class, in detail.
Thanks.