Hi, I'm Adam Porter and this is
Programming Mobile Applications For
Android Handheld Systems.
Today, I'm going to talk about the
fragment class.
Fragments were added to Android in version
3.0 to better support
user interfaces for the devices with large
screens, such as tablets.
Now, over the last few years,
the popularity of tablets have grown
incredibly
and as I'm sure you know tablets have
larger displays then phones typically do.
So, because of these larger screens
some of the design heuristics that made
sense for
a smaller phone display no longer work and
in particular
we can comfortably do much more on a large
tablet
display than we could do on a small phone
display.
Now, to put this in concrete terms, let's
take a look at a simple application called
QuoteViewer.
QuoteViewer is an applicatoin comprised of
two activities.
The first actiivity shows the titles of
several Shakespeare plays
and allows the user to select one title at
a time.
And when the user selects that title, a
second
activity is started, which displays one
quote from that play.
Let's take a look.
Here, I'll click on the launcher icon.
And now I'll launch the QuoteViewer
application.
The first activity starts up and shows us
the titles
of three Shakespeare plays: Hamlet, King
Lear, and Julius Caesar.
Let me click on Hamlet.
This starts the second activity, which
shows me Horatio's quote as
Hamlet is dying.
Now cracks a noble heart, Good-night,
sweet prince;
and flights of angels sing thee to thy
rest.
Now I'll hit the back button to return to
the titles.
And next I'll click on King Lear and again
we get a quote.
This time one from the blinded Earl of
Gloucester who says, as
flies to wanton boys, are we to the gods;
they kill us for
their sport.
And, once again, I hit the back button to
return to the titles, and this time,
I click on Julius Caesar, and again, the
second activity starts up and we see a
quote.
This one, where Brutus urges Cassius to go
on the attack.
He says, there is a tide in the affairs of
men, which taken at the flood leads on to
fortune.
Omitted, all the voyage of their life is
bound in shallows and in miseries.
Now this is a fine interface for a phone.
In fact, it would be hard to do much else
and still have a readable and easy to use
interface.
On a tablet however, this same layout is
pretty lame.
Now here, let me show you.
Here, I'm showing an emulated tablet.
I'll click on the launcher icon and now
I'll
start the QuoteViewer application we just
saw on the phone.
And the first thing you notice is all that
unused white space.
The titles take up just a little space on
the left
side of the display and the rest is pretty
much wasted.
Now, let me click on Hamlet.
And here you see that the
quote stretches all the way across the
10-inch
tablet, but uses little of the vertical
space.
Now I'll hit the back button to go back to
the titles
and I can do the same thing for the King
Lear quote, and
the same thing for the Julius Caesar
quote.
And besides not being, not using the
available space too well,
this layout imposes a slow back and forth
navigation style where the
user has to keep moving their hand from
the title, then down
to the back button, then back to the title
and so on.
So, let's see a better layout that uses
both
or shows both the titles and the quotes at
the
same time.
So here we are again, looking at an
emulated tablet.
I'll click on the launcher icon and
then start up the Fragment Static Layout
application.
And this initially brings up a user
interface that
looks exactly like what you saw with the
QuoteViewer application.
However, when I click on the title,
Hamlet, you see that the user
interface gets essentially divided into
two parts.
The titles stay were they were on the
left, but the
quote is now shown simultaneously on the
right side of the screen.
And now if I want to see a different quote
I simply select a new play tittle on the
left.
Here I'll select KIng Lear and again the
quote pops up on the right.
And the same thing when I select Julius
Caesar.
Now overall this layout works much better
on a tablet than QuoteViewer's layout
does.
In particular it avoids wasted space, and
it makes navigation a
little bit easier because I don't have to
keep moving my
hands down to the bottom of the display to
hit the
back button and then up to the titles and
so on.
The QuoteViewer application was made up of
two activities.
The Fragment Static Layout application
that we just
saw, however, is made up of a single
activity.
That single activity, however, hosts two
fragments.
Fragments represent a portion of an
activity's user interface.
The Fragment Static Layout application,
for example,
has two such interface portions.
One for the titles, goes on the left and
one for the quotes, that goes on the
right.
And each of these portions of the user
interface is implemented as a fragment.
Fragments are hosted by activities.
One activity can host zero or more
fragments.
And one fragment can be used across zero
or
more activities.
Now, as I said, fragments are posted by
activities.
So fragments have to be loaded into the
activity and then
displayed, removed and so on, as the
activity changes its state.
And as a result, the life cycle of a
fragment is tied
to and coordinated with the lifecycle of
the activity that's hosting it.
At the same
time, however, fragments have some of
their own lifecycle callbacks.
For now, let's talk about the fragment
lifecycle assuming
that the fragment is statically bound to
its hosting activity.
We'll talk about dynamically adding and
removing fragments
from a hosting activity a little bit
later.
So, a fragment can be in a running or
resumed state.
And what is in this state, the fragment is
visible in the running activity.
A fragment
can also be in a paused state, and
fragments will be paused when their
hosting activity is visible, but some
other
activity is in the foreground and has
focus.
A
fragment can also be in a stopped state.
In this state, the fragment is not
visible.
Let's talk now about the lifecycle
callback methods that
a fragment can receive and we'll talk
about when
those methods might be called relative to
the life
cycle states of the activity that hosts
the fragment.
When a fragment's hosting activity is
being created
the fragment may receive several lifecycle
method calls.
First, when a fragment is attached to its
hosting
activity, the fragment receives a call to
onAttach( ).
Next, the fragment receives a call to it's
onCreate( ) method.
And note here that I'm referring to the
Fragment.onCreate(
) method not the Activity.onCreate( )
method that
we've talked so much about in previous
lessons.
As with the activity.onCreate( ) method,
you typically
initialize the fragment in the fragment's
onCreate( ) method.
One difference between the two methods,
however, is that unlike in
activity.onCreate
( ), you don't set up the user interface
in fragment.onCreate( ).
That actually happens in the next method.
Now, after onCreate( ) Android calls the
fragment's onCreateView( ) method.
And this method sets up and returns a
view containing the fragment's user
interface, and this view
is then given to the hosting activity so
it
can install that view in the activity's
view hierarchy.
And finally, after the hosting activity
has been created and
the fragment's user interface has been
installed, then the
fragment receives a call to its
onActivityCreated( ) method.
Now, while the fragment is attached to the
hosting
activity its lifecycle is dependent on its
host lifecycle.
For example, if the hosting activity is
about to
become visible it will receive a call to
its onStart(
) method.
The fragment, therefore, will also receive
a call to its onStart( ) method.
When the hosting activity is about to
become visible and
ready for user interaction Android calls
the fragment's onResume( ) method.
And when the hosting activity is visible,
but another activity is about
to come in to the foreground, Android
calls the fragment's OnPause( ) method.
And when the hosting activity is no longer
visible, the fragment receives a call to
OnStop( ).
Now, when the hosting activity is about to
be destroyed any fragments that
it's hosting also have to be shut down,
and this happens in several steps.
First, when the fragment's user interface
view, the one that was
previously created by the call to
onCreateView( ), when that view has
been detached from that activity the
fragment receives a call to onDestroyView(
).
And here you can do things like clean up
resources associated with the view.
Next, when the fragment is no longer in
use,
it receives a call to it's onDestroy( )
method.
And here you can do things like, release
fragment resources.
Next, when the fragment is no longer
attached to its
hosting activity it will receive a call to
OnDetach( ).
And here you might do things like
null out references to the fragment's
hosting activity.