Hi.
I'm Adam Porter and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
So now that we've seen intents, let's talk
about how you use intents to start
activities.
Now if you remember back to the last
lesson, I talked about how
you could programmatically start an
activity using
methods such as startActivity or
startActivityFor Result.
Now when you use one of these methods,
Android has
to figure out which single activity it's
going to start up.
And there are two ways in which Android
does this.
The first way is that if you explicitly
named the target activity when you created
the intent, then Android can just look
that up and start that specific activity.
The second way, which is only used
if you haven't explicitly set the target
activity,
is that Android can implicitly determine
it based on the intent that was used and
based on the properties of activities that
you have installed on your device.
So
let's take a look at an application that
explicitly starts another activity.
And this application is called
HelloWorldWithLogin.
And it's comprised of two activities.
There's one activity called Login Activiy,
and another called Hello Android.
Now when this application launches, login
activity
is the first activity that is started.
Log in activity provides a text
box for typing in a username, and another
one for entering a password.
There is also a button, and once the user
enters
the username and password, they will hit
the log in button.
And then LoginActivity will check the
entered
pass, password and username, and if it
accepts
them, it will then start the
HelloAndroidActivity,
which will then display the words Hello
Android.
Let's see that
in action.
So
here's my device.
I'll go to the home screen, and then
I'll launch the hello android with log in
application.
This pops up a user interface screen,
allowing me to
enter a username and a password, now enter
that information.
And
now that I'm done, I'll click the log in
button.
If log in activity accepts my username
and password, then another activity
starts, displaying the
words, hello Android, so let's look at the
code to see exactly how this is
implemented.
I'll start by opening up the log in
activity class.
Here I'm showing the listener code
that's attached to the log in button and
here, the code
grabs the username and password that the
user has just entered.
And then passes them to a method called
check password.
If check password returns true, then the
code will continue.
First it creates an intent called hello
intent.
And as you can see, the call to the intent
constructor takes two parameters.
A context and a class object for the
activity to be started.
In this case, LoginActivity.this is used
as the context.
Now, a context is an interface that's used
to access global application information.
And since activity is a sub-class of
context, it's fine
to use LoginActivity.this for this
parameter.
The second parameter is the class object,
in this case for the Hello Android
activity.
This parameter indicates the activity to
be started by the call to start activity.
The
second way to start an activity is by
implicit activation.
In this situation, you haven't told
Android which activity to
start, so, it has to figure it out on its
own.
And what happens here is that Android
tries
to match the intent that was passed in to
start activity, or start activity for
result, with
the capabilities of activities that are on
your device.
And this process
is called intent resolution.
Intent resolution relies on two kinds of
information.
First, there's the intent, that the
calling activity created
to describe the operation that it wants to
be performed.
And second, individual Android activities
specify
intent filters which describe the kinds
of, of operations, or intents,
that they can handle.
And this information is usually placed in
the AndroidManifest.xml
file for the applications to which these
activities belong.
At runtime, when the start activity method
is actually called, Android will
try to match the intent with the intent
filters that it knows about.
However, it's only going use part of the
intent information
when it does this matching.
Specifically, it will look at the action
field, it will look at the data,
including both the URI and the MIME type,
and it will look at the category.
So let's take a look at how applications
specify intent filters within their
Android manifest .XML files.
So here's an XML snippet showing an
activity tag,
and this activity tag includes within it
an intent filter tag.
That intent filter tag includes within it
an action
corresponding to the intent action that it
can support.
For example, if an activity can dial phone
numbers, then
it should include an intent filter with
the standard action,
intent.action_dial.
Now that's the, the java name for that.
The actual value is, is really a string,
so you'll see android.intent.action.dial,
that's the value that will actually be
written into the intent filter.
If your activity handles a specific type
of data you
can add that information to its intent
filter as well.
For example, an activity can specify the
MIME type of data it handles, it can also
specify the scheme, host, and or port
number of the data URIs it handles.
It can further limit the format of the
data
URI by specifying its path, path pattern,
or path prefix.
And there are quite a few possibilities
here.
So please see the documentation
for more examples.
Now if an activity wants to publish that
it
can show maps for example, then it might
include an
intent filter like this one, which tells
Android that
it can handle data URIs that have a geo
scheme.
Similarly, activities can specify
categories for the intents they handle.
And let's look at an example that puts all
of this together.
Now, we can guess or imagine, based on
those map location applications we
saw before, that Google Maps can handle
intents, that have an action of
intent.action_view and that have a data
field with the geo scheme.
Now a while back I decided to take a look
at the Android manifest .XML file for the
Google Maps application.
And what I saw looked something like this.
There was an activity with an intent
filter.
And that intent filter just did an action
of intent.action.VIEW.
And, it had data, it had a data scheme of
geo.
In fact, this is exactly what
the MapLocation application's passed into
start activity.
So, going back to Google Maps,
the activity also listed two categories.
Category.browsable, meaning that it can
respond to browser links.
And category.default.
Now it turns out that in most cases
activities that want
to accept implicit intents must include
category.default in their intent filters.
And finally, more than one activity can
accept a particular
intent, Android will have to break the tie
in some way.
And one way to do that is just to ask the
user which activity
he or she wants to handle the intent and
you may have seen that.
Another possibility is that activities can
specify a priority.
That Android will take into account when
deciding between
two different activities that can handle a
particular intent.
Now those priority values should be
between minus 1,000 and positive 1,000.
And higher values mean higher priority.
Now for those of you who are interested in
knowing more about
intent filters, I recommend you take a
look at the adb dumpsys command.
Here, I've opened up a terminal window and
now,
I'll issue the command, adb shell dumpsys
package.
Now this is going to spit out a ton of
information from the package manager.
So I'll just capture the output of this
command into a text file.
Let's run the command and
now I'll open that file in a text editor.
I'll use emacs, and then we'll search for
the string geo.
And what you're seeing here, is that the
Google Maps application,
in fact, has an intent filter for URIs,
with the geo scheme.
So that's all for our lesson on intents.
Please join me next time, when we'll talk
about permissions.
Thank you.