Hi.
I'm Adam Porter, and this is Programming
Mobile Applications for Android Handheld
Systems.
There are two general ways that fragments
get added to activities.
First, they can be statically added to the
activity, for example, by putting them
into the activity's layout file which is
then used in a call to
set content view.
Alternatively, you can add
fragments programmatically using the
FragmentManager.
However they get added though, once
they're added,
Android will make a call to onCreateView,
and within
onCreateView, the fragment can use its own
XML layout,
similar to what activities do when they
call setContentView.
Or, they can programmatically build their
user interfaces.
And again, however it's done, once the
user interface view is built, onCreateView
must return the view that's at the root of
it's user interface layout.
And that view will eventually be given to
the hosting activity and added to the
hosting activity's user interface.
So, let's look back at the fragment
static layout application and see how it
defines its layout.
Here's the
application again.
And as you remember, there's a panel on
the left showing the
play titles and there's a panel on the
right showing quotes and
each of these panels is implemented by a
different fragment.
One is called title fragment and the other
is called quote fragment.
And this application's main activity is
called QuoteViewerActivity.
Let's open up the QuoteViewerActivity file
and
see how it handles or creates its layout.
Now, first, you'll see that in the
onCreate method, there's a call to
setContentView.
With a parameter value R.layout.main, so
let's look in the res/layout
directory for the file called main.XML.
Now here it is and let me open it up.
As you can see, the entire layout
is comprised of something called a linear
layout.
And that linear layout contains two
fragments,
and inside those fragment tags there's an
attribute called class.
And the value of this attribute is the
name of the class that implements that
fragment.
So in this case, one fragment is
implemented by the title fragment class.
And the other is implemented by the
QuotesFragment class.
Anyway, that's enough for now, we'll talk
more about layouts
when we get to user interfaces.
In any event, when this XML file is read,
Android will understand that it needs
to create these two fragments, and that it
needs to install them in the QuoteViewer
activity.
And this will start the chain of life
cycle calls that we talked about earlier.
And, as I said, one of those calls will
be a call to onCreateView, in which the
fragment
is responsible for creating its user
interface layout.
Let's take a look at one of those layouts,
the
one in QuoteFragment, to see how it
creates its user interface.
Now here's the QuoteFragment class, and
down here is its onCreateView method.
This method calls the inflate method of
the LayoutInflater class,
passing in a layout file as a parameter.
And the effect of this is pretty similar
to what happens in setContentView.
Specifically, an XML file is read in and
converted
into Java objects corresponding to some
user interface views.
You can also add fragments to an activity
without
hard coding the fragments into the
activity's layout file.
And to do that, while the activity is
running, you have to do four things.
One, get a reference to the fragment
manager.
Two, begin a fragment transaction.
Three, add a fragment to the activity.
And four,
commit the FragmentTransaction.
Now to see this in action, let's take the
fragment
static layout application, and change it a
bit so that
the fragments are added programatically,
rather than being added as
part of as part of the quote viewer's
layout file.
And here we are back in the IDE.
I've created
a new application called fragment
programatic layout, and
it's supposed to look exactly like
fragment static layout.
The only difference is how the fragments
get added to the main activity.
Let's open up the QuoteViewer activity and
see how it handles this layout.
Now here in onCreate, there's a call
to setContentView, with a parameter value
R.layout.main.
So let's look in the res/layout directory
for that main.xml file.
Now here it is.
Let me open it up.
Now as you can see, the entire layout is,
again, a linear layout with two sub views.
But instead of it being, the sub views
being
fragments, this time the sub views are
frame layouts.
The frame layout essentially reserve some
space in the user interface.
And we'll fill the space in later, when we
add the fragments to this activity.
Now let's go back to the on create method,
of quote viewer activity.
Now we'll walk through the steps of adding
the fragments into the user, into the
activity.
Now just like I said earlier, there are
four steps.
First, we get a reference to the fragment
manager, then we call the
begin transaction method on the fragment
manager, and that returns a fragment
transaction.
Next, we call the add method of the
fragment transaction.
Passing in an ID for the frame layout.
And passing in a fragment that that view
will hold.
And we'll do that for both the title
fragment and for the quote fragment.
And finally, we'll call the commit method
on the fragment transaction.
Now, let's run the code and make sure that
we haven't goofed anything up.
And here's the fragment programmatic
layout
application running on an emulated tablet.
And it seems to operate as promised.
So, now we know how to add fragments to an
activity programmatically.
But in our example, it didn't really make
that much difference
in the sense that, even though we added
the fragments programmatically.
The layout itself was static.
There are always exactly two panels, and
that never changes.
Now, one of the nice things about being
able to
add fragments on the fly, however, is that
it allows
you to dynamically change the user
interface while the program is running.
And if you do this right, it allows you
to make good use of your precious screen
space.
So, let's take a look at a simple example
that
gives you a little flavor of this dynamic
user interfaces,
again here's my emulated tablet and
I'll launch an application called
FragmentDynamicLayout.
Which again is similar to the previous
examples, but sometimes it
will show a single fragment and sometimes
it will show multiple fragments.
So here are the application.
We've just started it up and it's showing
a single fragment, is showing the title
fragment,
and nothing else.
And in fact, you can see that I've changed
the
title of Hamlet, to make it a little bit
longer.
And you can see that it takes up much more
of the screen space than before.
And in addition, if I click on that title,
you can see
that the item is indeed taking up the
whole, the entire screen horizontally.
Now that I finished clicking on the title
though, you can see
the familiar quote from Hamlet, and at
this point, the application is displaying
twp fragments.
If I now hit the back button, you see
that we've gone back to having just a
single fragment.
So let's take a look at the source code.
Now, here I am back in the IDE,
and I'll open up the fragment dynamic
layout application.
And we'll take a look at the quoteviewer
activity file.
Now first use the call the set content
view, passing in the main direct XML file.
And this is pretty similar to what we saw
before.
Next, we'll start the process of adding a
fragment to this activity.
This time, however, we'll only add the
title fragment.
In fact, we'll only ever add the quote
fragment if the user indeed clicks on a
title.
Now, supposing the user does click on the
title,
the on list selection method will then be
called.
Now let's take a look at that method.
First, we'll test to see if the quote
fragment has already been added to the
layout.
And if it hasn't, then we'll add it now,
by starting another fragment transaction.
So, two things are new here.
First, we're going to add this transaction
to the task back stack.
And that way, when the user hits the back
button, we'll go back to
the one fragment layout that we had before
it was, before it was added.
And we have to do this.
Because, by default, fragment changes are
not tracked by the back stack.
The second new thing is that at the end
I've added a call
to fragment manger.execute pending
transactions.
And this forces the transaction to be
executed immediately, rather than at
some later time when the system finds it
convenient to do so.
And again, I have to do this because
otherwise Android might, might
take, you know, God know how long before
it actually updates the display.
Now if you remember back to our lesson on
the activity class, I talked about
how activities can handle configuration
changes manually, using
methods such as on retain non
configuration instance.
And get last non-configuration instance.
And at that time, I mentioned that those
methods were
deprecated in favor of other methods in
the fragment class.
So, let's talk about those methods now.
Now, if you're using a fragment and
the device's configuration changes, then
android, by
default, will kill the hosting activity
and
recreate it just like we talked about
before.
However, if you call the set retain
instance method on the
fragment, passing in the value true as a
parameter, then when configuration
changes occur.
Android will kill the activity, but not
destroy the fragments that it's hosting.
Instead, it will save that fragment state
and
it will detach the fragment from the
activity.
And in addition, it won't destroy that
fragment and so
it won't recreate it later when the
hosting activity is recreated.
And as a result, the fragment
will not receive calls to its onDestroy
method nor to its onCreate method.
Let's take a look at another
example application that demonstrates this
behavior.
This application is called
FragmentStaticConfigLayout.
And its functionality is the same as the
previous examples.
The difference, here, though, is that I've
added some code to handle configuration
changes.
Now, when the device is in landscape mode,
the layout is basically what we've seen so
far.
Both fragments use a large font, size
32sp, or scale-independent pixels.
The title fragment takes about a third of
the horizontal space,
while the quote fragment takes the
remaining two-thirds of the space.
And, if a title is too long to fit on a
single line
in the title fragment, that text will
simply wrap around to a second line.
When the device is in portrait mode,
however, the layout changes a bit.
Both fragments use a smaller 24 sp font
and the TitleFragment takes up only a
fourth
of the horizontal space while the quote
fragment
takes up the remaining three quarters of
the space.
And, if a title
is too long to fit on a single line in the
TitleFragment, then that title will
still be limited to a single line, and
we'll just replace some of the text with
ellipses.
Let's see that application in action.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So here's an emulated tablet.
I'll start the application with the device
in landscape mode.
I'll select one of the titles to show a
quote.
And, as I said, the title fragment and
quote fragment will use larger fonts.
They're dividing up the screen in a
roughly one-fourth to three-fourths ratio.
And in the title fragment it's allowing
the title
of hamlet to spill over onto a second
line.
Now let's rotate the device, now one thing
that you notice is
that even though Android has killed and
restarted the quote viewer activity.
The title that I've previously checked is
still checked.
And that's because I made sure to call
setRetainInstance(true) in both fragments.
So information, for example, information
about which item
was checked, has been retained.
Now, we'll see how that's done in just a
second.
You'll also notice that now that we're in
portrait mode, the layout has changed.
In fact, the fonts are smaller now and
instead of that Hamlet title
spanning two lines, the end of the title
has been replaced with ellipses.
So let's go see how this works in the
code.
Now here I've opened
the fragment StaticConfigLayoutApplication
in the IDE.
Next I'll open up the TitleFragment.java
file, and
as you can see, this code is mostly the
same as what we saw in the other
example applications, but there are at
least two differences.
Let's look at those.
The first difference is in the onCreate
method.
I've added a call to setRetainInstance
True.
And again, this means that when
configuration
changes occur, Android will not kill this
fragment.
The second difference is in the on
activity created method.
And right here at the end I've added some
code
that checks to see whether m current index
is not
equal to minus 1, and if that's true, it
means
that the user has previously selected a
title and so
this call to on activity created, is
probably occurring because of a
configuration change.
So in this case, we want to make sure
that, that title remains checked now.
And I made similar changes to the quote
fragment class as well.
So that's all for our discussion of the
fragment class.
Please join me next time when we'll cover
Android user interfaces.
Thanks.