Hi, I'm Adam Porter.
And this is Programming Mobile
Applications For Android Handheld Systems.
In this lesson, I'll talk about how
Android applications can define and use
permissions, to control access to
important data, resources, and operations.
First, I'll talk about Android's
permissions architecture.
After that, I'll explain how you
can define and use application level
permissions.
And then, I'll finish up by talking about
component specific permissions and
permissions-related APIs.
Android uses permissions to protect
resources, data and operations.
And applications can also define and
enforce
their own permissions, to limit access to
their
resources and things like user
information, for example,
to restrict who can access an
application's database.
To cost-sensitive APIs, for example, to
restrict
which components can invoke costly
operations,
such as sending SMS or MMS messages.
And the system resources, for example to
limit which components
can use the device's camera, to take
pictures or record videos.
So, in Android, permissions are
represented as strings,
and applications include these permission
strings In the AndroidManifest.xml
file, and they can do this to declare the
permissions that they use themselves, and
to declare the permissions that they
require
of other components that want to use them.
Let's look at each of these uses of
permissions one at a time.
So first, when an application needs to use
a permission, it specifies that permission
by putting a  tag in it's
Androidmanifest.xml file.
And when that application is installed on
a
device, the user will have to accept that
permission.
Otherwise errors, or access failures will
occur.
Now here, I'm showing this snippet of the
android manifest
dot xml file for a hypothetical
application.
Now as you can see, this application needs
permission to access the device's camera.
Permission to open a network socket to
access the internet.
And permission to access precise location
information,
coming for example from a GPS provider.
Now, take a look at this documentation for
a list of Android's built in permission.
Now you probably remember the
MapLocationFromContacts application from
earlier lessons.
That application allows the user to select
a contact from the contacts application
and then to display a map centered
on that contact's postal address.
So here's the application in action.
So here's my device, Now I'll launch
the map location from contacts
application.
Now I see a button that will allow me to
select a contact.
When I click on that button, the contacts
application shows
me my contacts and allows me to select one
of them.
Once I do that, that contact's postal
address and other information is passed
to Google Maps, which then displays a map,
centered on the postal address.
And as I've said few times now, my contact
list is private information.
Android doesn't allow just any application
on my device to have access to that
list of contacts, so how did map location
from contacts get access to it?
That's right.
The application must have declared that it
uses the appropriate permission.
Where should we look to confirm that?
Again, that's right, we should look in the
Android manifest .xnl file.
Let's do that now.
So here I've opened up the map location
from contacts application in my IDE
now I'll open up the android manifest.XNL
file and we'll take a look inside.
As you can see there is a uses permission
tag.
That declares that this application uses
the built in read_contacts permission.
In addition to declaring the permissions
they use Android
applications can also define and enforce
their own permissions.
Now suppose that you've written an
application
that performs some privileged or dangerous
operation.
You might not want just any application to
to be able invoke yours so Android lets
you define and enforce your own
application specific permission and that
means that other applications must be
granted your permission
or Android will not allow them to use your
application.
Lets look at this in more detail with a
simple example.
So here's a simple application called
permission example boom.
Now were going to pretend that it performs
some kind of dangerous action.
In real life that might be something
like formatting your external memory card.
Now let's take a look at this application
in action.
Here's my device.
And nw I'll launch the permission example
boom application.
And boom goes the dynamite.
Now, since this operation is clearly
dangerous, we don't
want just anyone to be able to start this
application.
So we're going to define and enforce our
own application specific permission.
Now let's open up the AndroidManifest.xml
file to see how that's done.
So here's the permission example boom
application.
Now I'll open up the AndroidManifest.xml
file, and we'll take a look inside.
Here you can see a permissions tag that
defines the new permission.
The permission's name is
course.examples.permissionexample.boom_perm.
In this example, the permission tag
includes two other attributes, a label,
and a description which can
be shown to the user when they are
installing the application.
The values for these strings are in the
strings.xml file.
Now if we scroll down a bit, you can see
that this
application also includes this permission
as an attribute of the application tag.
And because of this,
Android will make sure that components
that try to
start this application have already been
granted the boom_permpermission.
Now since the permission example boom
application now requires the boom_
permission, any
other application that wants to use it
will first have to acquire that
permission.
So, let's see what happens if an
application without
the proper permissions tries to start
permission example boom.
So here I'm showing my device.
And I've installed a second application on
the device called Permission Example Boom
User.
And when I launch this application, it
presents a single button labeled Detonate.
And if I press this button, the Boom User
application will start up the Boom
application, which as I just showed,
requires the boom_perm permission.
The Boom User application, however, does
not have that permission.
So Android should prevent it from starting
up the Boom application.
Now before I press the detonate button,
I'll also point out that I've
opened the IDE and that it's showing log
output from the running device.
Okay.
So now, I'll press the detonate button.
And, as expected, something bad
has happened.
The device is showing an error dialog.
Telling the user that the boom application
has stopped and if we also go and look
at the log output, we can get more
information as to the cause of this
problem.
And as you can see in the log, Android has
thrown a security exception, saying that
boom user, requires the boom_permission.
So
let's fix that problem.
Now if boom user wants to use the boom
application, then it first has to declare
that it uses the boom_permission.
To do that, it will put a uses permission
tag in the AndroidManifest.xml file.
Let's see that in the code.
So here's the boom user application code,
and now it
will open up its AndroidManifest.xml file,
and here you can see
the users permission tag, with the name
attribute, whose value is
the same as the permission that's defined
by permission example boom.
Okay, so now that we've added the
users permission tag, I reinstalled the
permission
boom user application on my device, so let
me go to the home screen and launch it.
Now there's the detonate button again.
And so now I'll press it.
And boom goes the dynamite, as expected.
So so far, all the permissions I've shown
you have implied, have applied to the
entire application.
Android also allows you to set permissions
for individual components.
And these settings will take precedence
over any application level permissions.
Now let's take a look at some of these
component permissions.
Activity permissions restricts which
components
can start the associated activity.
These permissions are checked within the
execution
of methods such as startActivity() and
startActivityForResult().
Which as you know are called one activity.
Tries to start another one.
And if the required permission is missing,
then Android will throw a security
exception.
In fact, that's exactly what happened in
the permissions boom user example that we
just went over a few seconds ago.
Service permissions restrict which
components can start or bind to.
An associated service.
Now we haven't talk about services much
yet.
So, I'll just mention permissions, that
these
permissions are checked, when requests are
made
to start, stop or connect to services
using methods such as
Context.startService(),
Context.stopService(),
or Context.bindService().
Just as with activities, Android will
throw
a security exception if required
permissions are missing.
Broadcast receiver permissions restrict
which
components can send and receive
broadcasts.
Now again, we haven't talked about
broadcast receivers
very much yet, so at this point, I'll just
say that these permissions are checked in
a variety
of different ways at a variety of
different times.
And we'll talk more about this in later
lessons, when we discuss broadcast
receivers in more detail.
Content provider permissions restrict
which components can read and write the
data contained in a content provider.
And again, we'll talk more about this in
later
lessons when we discuss content providers
in more detail.
So that's all for this lesson on
permissions.
Please join me next time, when we'll
discuss Fragments.
Thanks.