Hi, I'm Adam Porter and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
In our last lesson, we talked about the
activity class
and I showed you how one activity can
programmatically start
another activity by first creating an
intent object, and then
by passing that intent to a method such as
start activity.
Or start activity for result.
Today, we're going to take a deeper look
at intents.
We'll discuss how they're created and
processed,
as they're used in starting other
activities.
And I'll begin by presenting the intent
class itself.
I'll talk about how they're created, what
fields
they have and what information those
fields contain.
After that, I'll talk about the two ways
in which Android decides which
activity should be stated when a method,
such as start activity, is called.
First, I'll talk about explicit
activation, in which intents specifically
name the activity they want to start.
And second, I'll talk about implicit
activation, where intents
don't select a target activity, but
instead describe the operation
they want to be performed after which
Android finds
and then starts the activity that can
perform that operation.
The intent class is basically
a data structure that serves at least two
purposes in Android.
One, it can specify an operation that you
want to perform and two, it can represent
an event that has occurred in the system
that you want to notify other components
about.
Today, however, we're going to focus on
just the first of
these, using intents to specify operations
that you want performed.
And we'll leave the second of these,
using intents for events notification, for
a
later lesson when we talk about broadcast
receivers.
Now, you can think about intents as
providing a kind
of language for specifying operations that
you want to have performed.
In essence, intents give you an easy way
to
say things like, I want to select a
contact.
I want to take a photo.
I want to dial a phone number, or I want
to display a map.
And so in practice, intents are usually
constructed
by one activity that wants some work to be
done, and then Android uses that intent to
start another activity that can perform
the desired work.
So let's talk now about the kinds of
information that can be specified within
an intent.
For example, we'll talk about intent
fields including action, data, category,
mine
type, target component, extras and flags.
An intent's action field is a string that
represents or names the operation to be
performed.
Some built in examples include
action_dial, which means,
I want someone to dial a phone number.
Action_Edit.
I want someone to display some data for
the user to edit.
Action_Sync.
I would like to synchronize some data on
my device with data on a server.
And Action_Main.
I want to start an activity as the initial
activity of an application.
You can set an intent's action in several
ways.
For example, you can pass an action string
as a parameter to the intent constructor.
Alternatively, you can create an empty
intent, and then, call the set
action method on it, passing the action
string, again as a parameter.
Intents also have a data field which
represents data that is associated with
the intent.
That data is formatted as a Uniform
Resource
Identifier, or URI.
And one example of intent data
is a geo schemed URI.
Which indicates map data.
You might also remember that we saw
something exactly like
this in earlier lessons as part of those
MapLocation applications.
Another example is the tel schemed URI
indicating a phone number that you want
dialed.
And note that the strings that represent
the underlying data are first being passed
through the uri.parse method which takes
that
string and then returns an URI object.
You can set the intent's data in a variety
of ways.
For instance, you can pass it directly to
the intent's constructor or you
can create an empty intent and then use
the set data method to set
the data for that intent.
Intent category represents additional
information about the kinds of
components that can handle or should
handle this intent.
Some examples include category_browsable.
Which means that the activity can be
invoked by a browser, via a URI link.
Another example is category_launcher,
which means that the target
activity can be the initial activity of a
task, and is listed in the top-level
application launcher.
Intents also have a type field, which
specifies the mime type of the intent's
data.
Some examples of mime types include
various image formats, things like,
image/png for png images, and image/jpg,
or jpg,
for jpg images.
There are also various text formats such
as text/html for html text, or text/plain
for arbitrary text data.
And of course, if you don't specify a mime
type, Android will try to infer one for
you.
You can set an intent's mime type by using
the set type method.
Passing in a string that represents the
desired mime type.
You can also set both the data and the
type together by calling the
setDataAndType method.
Intents also have a component field that
identifies the intent's target activity.
And you can set this field, if you
know that there's exactly one activity
that should always receive this intent.
You can set the intent's target component
using
one of the intent's constructors, by
passing in
a context object and a class object which
represents the activity that should
perform the desired operation.
And we'll see a code example of this in a
few minutes.
You can also create an empty intent and
then use one
of the set component, set class, or set
class name methods,
to set that target activity.
Intents also have an extras field.
Extras store additional information
associated with the intent.
Now extras are effectively a map of key
value pairs.
And so the target activity has to know
both the name and the type
of any extra data that it intends to use.
For example, the intent class, defines an
extra called extra_email.
And this extra is used to pass a list of
recipients in sending email.
As you can see here, this code creates an
intent with the action intent.action_send.
If we want to send some email.
It also
adds an extra to that intent.
The extra is named
EXTRA_EMAIL.
And in this case its values include
me, aporter@cs.umd.edu, ceo@microsoft.com,
potus@whitehouse.gov, and Mozart, at
musician.org.
Now, there are several different methods
for setting
extras, and the specific form of these
methods will
depend on the type of data you want to
store.
So, for example, there is method for
storing a string,
one method for storing an array of floats,
and so on.
Another intent field is called flags.
Flags represent information about how the
intent should be handled.
Some built in examples include
FLAG_ACTIVITY_NO_HISTORY.
Which means that when an activity is
started, based on this intent, it
shouldn't be put in the history stack.
Another flag is FLAG_DEBUG_LOG_RESOLUTION.
Which tells Android to print out extra
logging information when this intent is
being processed.
And this is a great tool to use if your
intents
are not starting up the activities that
you want them to.