Hi, I'm Adam Porter, and this is
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems.
In this lesson, we're going to talk about
the many different kinds of classes
that Android gives you to help you
build good looking and effective user
interfaces.
In particular, I'll start by introducing
the view class.
A basic
building block for just about everything
that's visible on your device's screen.
I'll also discuss the various events that
views can receive.
After that, I'll discuss a higher level
compound view called groups, called View
Groups which combine multiple views to
create a particular look or behavior.
I'll also discuss some specific view
groups.
In particular AdapterViews, and Layouts.
And after that, I'll talk about menus
and the action bar, which give users easy
access to frequently used functions.
And last, I'll finish up with the
discussion of Dialogs.
Those views that popup in front of an
application,
to give and get information to and from
the user.
So let's talk about user interfaces or
UI's in general.
First of all, a user interface is
essentially the place and
the means by which the user and the
application exchange information.
And in this lesson, when I talk about a
UI, I'm specifically going to concentrate
on the device screen, and the visual
elements that users can see and
touch on that screen.
But of course modern user interfaces can
be much more than just that.
Now for instance, hand held devices
typically have many sensors.
So user interfaces increasingly leverage
many different
kinds and qualities of input and output.
Including audio, LED lights, radio waves
and more.
Now getting
back to Android.
As I said before, activities usually
display
a visual user interface to the user.
So Android provides a rich set of classes
from which developers can create those
user interfaces.
Let's talk about some of those classes
starting with the view class.
The view class is a key building block for
UI components.
Views occupy a rectangular space on the
screen, and they're responsible
for drawing themselves and for handling
any events that are directed to them.
Android comes with a number of predefined
or built-in views.
Let me talk about a couple of them.
Specifically, I'll talk about Buttons,
ToggleButtons, Checkboxes, the RatingBar,
and the AutoCompleteTextView.
So we've seen lots of buttons already in
this class.
A button is just a view.
It's usually a somewhat small view that
users can
click on to start or to perform some
action.
Let's see one in the UI button
application.
So let me start up this simple
As you can see it's called UIButton, and
it has
a single button at the the bottom of the
screen.
And that button is labeled Press Me.
And if you give into the
temptation and press the button, you'll
see that the label changes,
and now says got pressed, followed by the
number of times
that button has been pressed so far.
So, I'll press it a few more times, and
you
can see that the count continues to rise by
one, each
time that I press the button, And by now,
you
can probably guess what the code for this
activity looks like.
In fact you've seen lots of examples in
previous lessons that do things just like
this.
The code for this activity has created
a button object and its attached to a
listener to that button.
And every time I press this button,
Android promises to
and in fact does call the button
listener's onClick method.
Let's look at some more built in views,
and then I'll stop and give
you some time to look at the code for each
of the sample applications.
The next view is called the ToggleButton.
A ToggleButton is a kind, is another kind
of button, however, it
also has the extra property that when you
press it, it stays pressed.
And it stays pressed until you press it
again.
So a ToggleButton is always in one of two
states.
It's either checked or it's not checked.
ToggleButton's also typically display some
kind of indicator to
let the user know what this, what state
the button is currently in.
And you've probably seen toggle buttons
likes
this in many applications such as music
players.
You hit the button and the music starts
playing,
and it continues playing until you hit the
button again.
Let's see a ToggleButton in action.
I'll start the Toggle, the UIToggleButton
application.
And the application starts up, and
shows a single, unchecked ToggleButton,
labeled Start.
Under the label there's a small area.
It's not lit up right now.
But it will light up when the toggle
button is eventually checked.
So the idea here is that something's
going to
start happening when the user presses this
ToggleButton.
So, I'll hit the Start button now.
And what happens?
In this case, the background color changes
from
black to white, and the ToggleButton now
says Stop.
You can see there's also a small blue
highlight underneath
the label, which indicates that the
ToggleButton is now checked.
The next view I'll talk about is the
checkbox.
And you've probably seen things like this
in many applications.
Things like order forms, where for
instance, you check all the
toppings that you want on your pizza, or
something like that.
Now a checkbox is actually just another
kind
of two state button, just like a toggle
button.
The main difference is just what it looks
like to the user.
Checkboxes usually display some kind of
area that's empty
when the checkbox is not checked, but
shows a
check mark or an x symbol or something
like
that, when the check box is in the checked
state.
Let's see a checkbox in action.
So here's my phone's home screen, and now
we'll start the UI Checkbox application.
The application starts up, And going from
top to bottom, displays some text,
and then an unchecked check box followed
by the words, I'm not checked.
And then underneath all that, there's a
button that says, Hide
CheckBox.
Now, I'll click on the checkbox.
And as you can see, it displays a check
mark to show that it has now been
selected.
You'll also notice that the text following
the checkbox has changed to say, I'm
checked.
And as you can imagine in the source code,
I've attached a listener to the checkbox.
Which changes that text to reflect the
checkbox's
current state.
Now, I'll click on the Hide CheckBox
button.
And when I do that, the listener attached
to the button
changes the visibility of the checkbox so
that now it's invisible.
When I click on the button again, the
check box becomes visible again and again.
When we take a break, please walk through
the code for all of these sample
applications to get an idea or see
the different ways that views can be
manipulated.
The next view is the RatingBar.
This view displays a row of stars like
you might use in a application that rates
restaurants or songs, or things like that.
You know, it's great, I gave it five stars
out of five,
or aw, that's awful I gave it one star out
of five.
The RatingBar allows users to highlight
some number of
stars by clicking or dragging on the
RatingBar view.
Let's see an application that uses a
RatingBar.
Now I'll start the UIRatingBar
application.
I've set up the RatingBar to show a
total of four stars, all unselected at the
beginning.
Now I'll select the first star and as you
can see it highlights.
Now the second star, and now the third.
And now I'll drag back across the
RatingBar, which essentially deselects all
the stars.
And the
last view I'll talk about is the
AutoCompleteTextView.
This view is first of all a text view.
That is, it's a view that displays text.
And we've seen lots of those already.
This text view is also editable,
which means that users can type text that
will go into this text view.
And in addition, this view will show a
list of text
entries and will filter that list, as you
type, so
that it only shows those entries that
match what you're typing.
And once you've narrowed down the list,
you can touch a
single entry which will then be placed
into the text view.
Let's see that in an application.
Back to my phone.
I'll start up the UIAutoComplete
application.
This application shows the words Country,
and
then next to that there's an
AutoCompleteTextView.
And I've associated a long list of
countries with this AutoCompleteTextView.
And now I want to have the name Chile
appear in this box.
Now
I could have put the list in some kind of
scrolling view, but then I would've
had to you know, keep scrolling through
the
long list to find the country that I
wanted.
With an AutoCompleteTextView however, I
don't have to do any scrolling.
I can just tart, start typing in some
letters For instance,
here I'll type the letter C, and now the
letter H.
And as you can see, there's a drop down
list that
has appeared, showing only those countries
that start with the letters CH.
So in this case, there's Chad, Chile,
China, and the
Christmas Islands.
So I'll continue by typing the letter I.
And now the list has shrunk to just Chile
and China.
Now I'll go ahead and type one more letter
L, and now
there's just the single country Chile, and
that's left in the drop down list.
So I'll just select it now.
And as you can see, the world
Chile has been inserted into the
AutoCompleteTextView.
And a little message window pops up
confirming that I've chosen Chile.
So those are a few of the views that
Android provides.
In the example application showed some of
the operations that are commonly applied
to views.
For instance, the UICheckbox application
changes the visibility of the checkbox.
The UIToggleButton and UICheckbox
applications changed
the check state of the view.
And also
all of the examples used listeners in
various ways to take some kind of action
once the user has manipulated the view.
Your own applications of course.
You'll put your own applications specific
code in those listeners.
And there are also many other view
operations that we didn't show.
For instance, you can set a view opa,
opacity or transparency.
You can set
it's background.
It's orientation on a display.
And other things.
And you can also have your viewers
interact
with the keyboard by requesting or
accepting the
input focus which tells Android that
keyboard clicks,
for example, should be sent to a
particular view.
Views handle events, and these events can
come from various sources.
Including the user
when he or she touches a view on the
display or
uses physical input devices, such as a
physical keyboard, trackball or D-pad.
Android itself can also be a source of
events.
For instance, views receive various method
calls when
Android needs to reposition or re-draw the
views.
Let's talk a bit more about view events.
As we've seen
many times already, a very common way to
handle events
is by attaching the, is by attaching
listeners to individual views.
Android defines a number of different
kinds of listener interfaces.
And the methods defined by those
interfaces get called when specific events
occur on a view.
For example, the view class defines an on
click listener interface that has an
onClick method.
This method is called whenever a view has
been clicked.
The view class also defines the
onLongClickListener, and that has an
onLongClick method.
And this method is called whenever a view
is
pressed and held pressed for a specific
period of time.
The view class also defines that
onFocusedChangeListener, that has an
onFocusChange method,
and this method is called when a view has
received or lost focus.
It also defines an onKeyListener interface
that has an onKey method which
is called when the view is about to
receive a hardware key press.
And there are many other events that you
can listen for as well.
So let's step back for a second.
Right now, we're talking about individual
views.
But applications typically involve many
views,
all being displayed at the same time.
As we saw when we used the UIHierarchy
viewer in our lesson on
the Android development environment, and
applications
views are typically organized as a tree.
Now, there's some outer most view, and it
holds some
number of child views.
And each of those child views can have
it's own children.
And so on, so on.
When Android goes to draw all these views
on the screen, it does so by walking
through this view tree multiple times,
each time doing something a bit different.
So, conceptually, on the first pass, it
measures all of the views.
On the second pass, it positions all the
views.
And on the third pass, it draws all the
Now much of the time, you don't worry or
care about these steps.
But, if you create your own custom view
sub-classes, then you may also want to
override these various
view methods to ensure that your custom
view is
drawn the way that you want it to be.
For instance, when its doing its measuring
pass, Android will call onMeasure on your
view.
And your view must calculate and then set
its own dimensions.
When its doing its layout pass, Android
will call your views onLayout method.
And this method should position itself and
call layout on all of its children view.
During the third pass, Android will call
your views'
onDraw method and this method then draws
the view.
Some other method you might want to
override in your custom
views, include onFocusChanged, to handle
when your view's focus state changes.
OnKeyUp or onKeyDown, to handle hardware
key events.
Or, onWindowVisibilityChanged, to handle a
change in the
visibility status of the window containing
your view.