[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi, I'm Adam Porter and this is
Programming Mobile
Applications for Android Handheld Systems.
Adapter
views are generic ViewGroups that are used
to display a list of data.
Layouts are generic ViewGroups that are
used
to organize and structure other views in
ViewGroups.
For example, consider the linear layout.
This ViewGroup holds a set of child views
or ViewGroups, but it arranges the
children in a single row, either
horizontally or vertically.
Let's look at an example.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Here's an application called
UILinearLayout.
And what you see here is a set
of colored boxes labeled red, green, blue,
and yellow.
And they're all laid out in a horizontal
row.
Under that, there's another set of boxes
laid out vertically.
And they're labeled row one,
row two, row three, and row four.
So let's look at the source code to see
how that layout was actually created.
Here's the UI layout application.
And I'm going to go straight to the main
.XML file where its layout is stored.
In
this file, you see that the entire layout
is a LinearLayout.
And that LinearLayout has two children,
each of which is also a LinearLayout.
Now the outermost linear layout has a
layout_width and
a layout_height of match_parent.
And this means that it takes
up all of the space of its parent, in this
case, the entire application window.
And you can also see that its orientation
is vertical.
And this means that the children will be
layout,
will be laid out one on top of the other.
Now, if we look at the first
child LinearLayout, we see that its
layout_width is match_parent.
So it should be as wide as the parent, the
outermost LinearLayout.
Its layout_height, however, is set to 0.
It also has a layout_weight of 1, and
we'll see
how these bits of information are used in
a minute.
The last thing to notice is that the
orientation is horizontal.
So, the children of this LinearLayout will
be laid out next
to each other horizontally.
Now,
let's go to the second child of that
outermost LinearLayout.
And it again is also a LinearLayout.
And this element has a layout_width
of match_parent and a layout_height of 0.
Its layout_weight,
however, is 3, whereas that first child
had a layout_weight of 1.
And these weights tell Android that the
first child LinearLayout should get one
fourth of the space, while the second
child gets the remaining three fourths.
The second child also has an orientation
of vertical rather than horizontal.
The next layout is a RelativeLayout.
With a RelativeLayout, child views are
positioned relative to each other and to
their parents, rather than in a fixed
order, as we saw with the LinearLayout.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Here's the UIRelativeLayout application.
This application contains an EditText view
and two buttons.
Let's look at how we get that particular
layout.
Now here's the UI RelativeLayout
application.
Now let's open up the main.xml layout
file.
As you can see, we've got a RelativeLayout
as the outermost ViewGroup.
Inside it, there are the elements that we
saw on the screen.
An EditText field and two buttons.
And they're labeled OK and Cancel.
And if we look more closely, we can see
that the
OK button should be aligned to the right
of the parent.
That's the RelativeLayout.
And below the EditText, which is
designated by
its ID entry.
Now the Cancel button says that it should
be aligned to the left of the OK button,
and that its top should be aligned with
the top of the OK button.
So, putting all those constraints together
then, Android is able to come
up with the layout that you saw when we
ran the application.
The next layout is a TableLayout.
With a TableLayout, child views are
arranged into rows and columns.
Here, I'll start up the UITableLayout
application.
This application mimics an old text-based
menu, which
you see is laid out, one command per row.
And within each row, the different pieces
of information are laid out in columns.
In the IDE, we can open up the layout
file.
And here we can see that the layout is a
TableLayout,
and that within the TableLayout, there are
a number of table rows.
Within each table row, there's a list of
views.
And these views are assumed to be in
numerical column order.
But if necessary, you can specify a
layout_column.
For instance, this row has nothing in
column 0, so we have to tell Android
that the first row's text view should go
in column 1, not in column 0.
And you can also see that this TextView
specifies a gravity of right,
which means that the views text should be
pushed to the right of the TextView.
The
next layout is the GridView.
GridViews arrange their children in a two
dimensional, scrollable grid.
So I'll start up the UIGridView
application.
This application reads in a bunch of
images and
then automatically lays them out in a
rectangular grid.
And when I click on any one of these
images, another activity is started, that
displays that single image.
Let's look at the source code now.
So here I've got the UIGridView
application open in the IDE.
I'll open its main.xml layout file.
And in that file, you see that there's a
GridView element.
In that element, I've specified some
things such as the width of
the columns, and the amount of spacing to
leave around each image.
I also specify that the GridView
is free to determine the number of columns
to use.
Now going to the source code, I'll open up
the GridLayout activity file.
In there, you can see that I've specified
a list of image resources.
This should be displayed by the GridView.
Down in onCreate, I set the ContentView,
and then set the adapter, which is an
instance of the ImageAdapter class.
Let's look at the ImageAdapter class.
First, ImageAdapter is a
subclass of BaseAdapter, which ultimately
implements the adapter interface.
This class has several methods that get
used when
the GridView is asking for data and for
data views.
Let's go through a few of this class's
methods.
First, there's the getCount method.
This method should return the number of
data items managed by the adapter.
Another method is getItemId, and this
returns an
ID for the data item in a specified
position.
And this gets used, for instance, when the
user clicks on an image in the GridView
to indicate which image to load when the
larger individual view pops up.
The last method I'll talk about is
GetView.
This method gets called when GridView asks
the adapter for one view
that will go into the grid.
One of the parameters for this method is a
view called ConvertView.
And this parameter will sometimes be no.
If so, then you need to create a new view
and configure it however you want.
But other times,
ConvertView will not be null.
It will actually reference a view that was
already returned by this method in the
past.
For example, if you have a lot of views in
the grid and only some of them might
be visible at any one time, so GridView
will
only ask for the views that it's going to
display.
But if the user later scrolls to
GridView, some of the views that were
visible are
going to become invisible because they
scroll off the screen.
So Android will try to reuse those views,
and it will pass one of those
new views off to the adapter to get to the
GetView method.
Then you'll just use that view and reset
whatever fields that you
need for your current data item.
And this is good because it saves the time
needed to allocate
new views, which in turn can make the
scrolling look much more fluid.
The next thing I'll talk about are Menus
and the ActionBar.
Activities can support Menus.
Menus can be presented to the user in
different ways.
But the basic
idea is that Menus give users a quick way
to access
important functions.
So, activities can add items to a Menu,
and they can respond when the user invokes
the Menu item, say by clicking on it.
Now, the appearance of Menus has changed
in Android over time,
so I'll talk about basic menus first, and
then later I'll
talk specifically about the newer
ActionBar class.
Now there are three kinds of Android
menus.
First, there are Options Menus, which are
shown when a user presses the menu button.
Older Android devices usually had a
dedicated physical menu key.
Newer ones don't.
Second, there are Context Menus.
And these menus are attached to specific
views and are
shown only when the user presses and holds
that view.
Context Menus are usually used for
operating
on the specific data held in the view,
while Option Menus and SubMenus tend to be
for global operations that affect the
whole application.
And third, there are SubMenus.
And these are secondary menus that are
only activated
when the user touches an already visible
menu item.
Let's look at some examples of these.
So
here's the Phone application.
Let me show you an example of an Options
Menu for this application.
First, I'll scroll over
to the Contacts tab, and you can see that
there's an icon here at the bottom.
And when I click on it, a menu pops up,
allowing me to do things
like, specify which contacts to display,
or import or
export contacts.
Next, let's see an example of a Context
Menu.
I'll open the Browser application and use
an
Options Menu to get to the bookmarks
functionality.
Now that brings up a tab showing
bookmarks, history, and saved pages.
I'll select History, which shows me a list
of web pages that
I've visited recently.
And now I'll press and hold on
one of these web page history entries.
And as you can see, that brings
up a new menu, supporting actions that can
be applied to this one webpage link.
Things like opening it, bookmarking it, or
sharing it.
And last, let me show you an, let me show
you an example of a SubMenu.
Here I'll open the Gallery application,
which shows me some photo albums stored on
my device.
I'll click on one and now I see a photo
from the album.
I'll click on the Menu ic, icon, which
presents a set of actions that I can
perform.
I'll select the Delete menu option.
Now this brings up a secondary menu, which
actually
gets shown as a kind of dialog in this
case,
asking me to confirm the deletion.
Now in order to create the Menus, you
first define the contents of the menu in
an XML file in the res/menu directory.
When the user later opens the menu,
Android calls a particular method,
such as onCreateOptionsMenu for Options
Menus and their
SubMenus, or onCreateContextMenu for
Context Menus.
In these methods, you'll use a
MenuInflater to create the actual menu
layout.
When the user later selects one of the
menu items, Android will call a method,
such as onOptionsMenuItem selected for
Options Menus and SubMenus,
or onContextMenuItem selected Context
Menus.
Let's look
at a simple example with all these
different kinds of menus.
This application is called HelloAndroid
WithMenus.
I'll start it up and as you can
see, there's a TextView with the words
Hello Android.
And if I press and hold this TextView, a
Context Menu will pop up.
And this one simply tells me to hit the
menu button instead.
So let's try that.
Now, if you look up in the top right
corner, you
can see the icon that gets you to the menu
items.
And I'm calling that icon a menu button,
but
actually it's an overflow area for actions
that appear
on the ActionBar, which is in the area,
which
is the area at the top of the application.
So, let me click on that icon,
and this brings up a menu with three
entries.
Help, more help, and still more help.
And if I click on these, some actions will
be taken.
Now for the first two menu entries, I just
display some texts on the screen.
The last one, however, is associated with
a SubMenu, which in this case just
has one entry, telling me there is no more
help.
Let's look at how this is implemented in
the source code.
And here we are in the IDE.
And I'll open up the
HelloAndroidWithMenuActivity file.
And first, we'll look at the
onCreateOptionsMenu method.
In this method, we get the MenuInflater,
and then call its inflate method
passing in a reference to the menu layout,
and passing in the menu in
which we want to put the new layout.
Now
I'll open the menu file top_menu.xml.
And this file contains a menu tag.
And inside it, there are
several item tags.
In each tag, there are
attributes, such as an ID, an icon to
display for
this item, and a title for this item.
The third Menu
item also includes a SubMenu, which is
specified by the nested menu tag.
Back in the activity.
In the last line of onCreateOptionsMenu,
we'll return the value
true, indicating that we want to display
this Menu item now.
Now when the users selects one of these
Menu items,
Android will call onOptionsItemSelected,
passing in the selecting item.
Here, we check the item's ID and then take
the appropriate action for that item.
Now let's look at how the Context Menu is
set up.
First, when a user invokes the Context
Menu for the first time, Android calls
onCreateContextMenu.
The code is very similar to what we saw
with the Options Menu.
You get the
MenuInflater and you use it to inflate an
XML layout file.
Let's open it up.
Now this menu just has a single item with
the ID help_guide.