[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hi.
I'm Adam Porter, and this is Programming
Mobile Applications for Android Handheld
Systems.
>> So, so far we've been talking mostly
about individual views.
But in reality, we often want to have some
kind of compound view,
that puts together multiple individual
views,
in order to provide some complex
functionality.
A simple
example that we'll talk about in a minute,
is a Radio Group.
A Radio Group is essentially a set of
related check boxes.
For example, you might have an application
that asks how old you
are, and allows you to select from a set
of age ranges.
Say, under 20, 20 to 34, 35 to 49, and
over 50.
And to do this,
you would have a bunch of text views for
all
the different age ranges, and then next to
each text view.
You put a check box.
Now you'd also want to make sure that only
one of those check boxes is ever selected.
Because the age ranges obviously are
mutually exclusive.
To support complex views like this,
Android has a class called Viewgroup.
Viewgroups are invisible views, that
contain other views.
And so you can use them to group and
organize multiple views and view groups.
ViewGroup is a base class for View
Container and Layouts, which
we'll discuss, you know, in more detail
later on in this lesson.
Just like with simple views, Android
provides a number of predefined view
groups.
Including some we'll talk about now such
as, RadioGroup, TimePicker, DatePicker,
WebView, MapView, Gallery, and Spinner.
Let's take a look at each of these one at
a time.
Let's start with the RadioGroup.
As I just explained a RadioGroup is a
ViewGroup containing
a set of mutually exclusive check boxes or
Radio Buttons.
So only one of the Radio Buttons can be
selected at any one time.
Let's take a look at an example
application.
So here's my phone.
[SOUND] And now I'll start up the UI
RadioGroup application.
The application displays a TextView and a
RadioGroup.
The TextView is displaying the text no
choice made.
Because right now none of the radio
buttons are selected.
So now I'll select choice one and as you
can see the text
changes to reflect the choice that I made.
Now I'll select choice two.
And again you can see that choice one,
was automatically unselected and choice
two was now selected.
And the same kind of thing happens when I
select Choice three.
The
next ViewGroup is TimePicker.
And this Viewgroup allows the user to
select a particular time.
Again, here's my phone, I'll now start up
the UITimePicker application.
And the application displays a text view
showing the current time.
And a button labeled Change the Time.
So I'll click on the button.
And, up pops the time picker view group.
As you can see, the time picker is
composed of many different views,
that together allow the User to
independently set the hour, the
minutes, and whether or not the time is
a.m or p.m.
There's also a button at the bottom to
indicate that you're done.
And once you click that button, the text
view
changes to show the time that you just
selected.
Similar to the TimePicker, there is also a
DatePicker ViewGroup.
This ViewGroup allows the user to select a
particular date.
So now I'll start the UIDatePicker
application.
The application displays a text view
showing the
current date and a button labeled change
the date.
So
I'll click on the button and up pops the
DatePicker ViewGroup.
Again, the DatePicker is composed of many
different views,
that together allow the user to
independently
set the month, the day, and the year.
And there's also a button at the bottom to
indicate when you're done.
When you click on that button, the text
view changes,
to show the date that you selected with
the DatePicker.
The next View group is a WebView.
A WebView is a ViewGroup that displays Web
pages.
Here's the UI WebView application.
I'll start it up.
And it will download and display the
familiar web page at
www.google.com.
The next view group is a MapView.
And as the name suggests,
a MapView is a ViewGroup, that displays
maps.
And allows the user to interact with them.
Let's take a look at an example
application that actually uses the
map fragment class but uses it to display
the underlying and underlying MapView.
So
now I'll start up the UIGoogleMaps
application.
Once it's started up.
This application displays a map centered
on some part of the America's.
The map also displays two red pins.
One, around Washington D.C. in the United
States and
another in Mexico.
Let me click on the upper most red pin.
When I do that pop up appears saying I'm
at the Washington Monument.
If I then click on the other red pin, I
see another pop up.
This time saying estoy Mexico.
I'm in Mexico.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now the view groups I just showed you,
each have a fairly clear
purpose, and for the most part, work with
a fixed kind of input data.
The next set of view groups that I want to
discuss, are designed
for situations where different developers
nay
want to display different kinds of data.
Consider, for instance, a list view, which
can be
used to show a list of phone numbers to
dial,
a list of songs to play, a list of
images to select as your phone's
wallpaper, and so forth.
In order for ViewGroups like list view to
work with all these different data types.
Android provides a ViewGroup subclass
called AdapterView.
AdapterViews are View-Groups whose child
views and underlying data are
managed not by the View-Group itself but
by another class called an Adapter.
And this Adapter class is responsible for
managing the data and for creating and
providing
the views of that data to the Adapter
View, when the AdapterView ask for them.
The AdapterView then is only responsible
for displaying the data views.
So let's
take a deeper look at the list view class
that I just talked about.
ListView is an AdapterView that displays a
scrollable list of selectable items.
Those items are managed by an adapter
called the ListAdapter.
The ListView can also optionally filter
that list of items based on Text Input.
Just like what we saw with the auto
complete text view.
So let me start up the UIListView
application.
And as you can see the data underlying
this list view is a long list of colors.
Red, Orange, Yellow.
Et cetera.
And this list also brings up a virtual or
soft keyboard.
And I'll use it to type in the letter o.
And as I do this the ListView will filter
all
of the colors that don't start with the
letter o.
In this case, that leaves just orange and
olive.
I'll now type in the letter L, which
leaves just the color olive.
And if I click on that word olive, you'll
see that the listener
I've attached to the list view will
display my selection on the screen.
Let's take a look at the source code for
this application.
Now here I've opened the application in
the IDE.
Now I'll open up the file
ListViewActivity.
And let's go to the onCreate method.
Here, we're calling setListAdapter, to set
the list adapter for this ListView.
The actual adapter is an array adapter
which implements the adapted Interface.
The constructor for the array adapter
takes a few parameters.
The two that we'll focus on are the
resource ID,
which tells the array adapter how to
create the view.
Containing each piece of data, and the
array
of data objects itself is the second
parameter.
Let's look at those data objects.
They're defined as a string array resource
in the res/values/strings.xml file.
And here you can see the string array,
it's named colors, and it
contains a bunch of colors, just like we
saw, red, orange, yellow, and so forth.
Now let's go back to the list view
activity, and get the name of the Layout
file,
that will be used to create views for each
of these colors.
That Layout resource is in
res/layout/list_item.xml.
Let's open that file.
Now as you can see, each piece of data, is
going to be
put in the text view, with the certain
amount of padding around it,
And each drawing with the certain font
size.
Now, back to the list view activity.
The next bit of source code, gets the list
view associated
with the list activity, and then calls set
text filter enabled, true.
And this causes the keyboard to popup.
And then filtered to occur when the User
types.
And then,
finally, we set an On Item clicked
listener.
Which has an On Item clicked method.
And
that method will display the color that
the User selects when they click on the,
or by clicking on the ListView.
The next AdapterView is the Spinner class.
A spinner is an adapter view that provides
a
scrollable list of items within a drop
down view.
The user can click on this AdapterView.
Which causes a Drop Down
list to appear, and then allows the User
to select an item from that drop down
list.
And the data for a spinner is managed by a
Spinner Adapter.
Let's take a look at this class in an
example application.
Now here I'll start up the UISpinner
application.
And this brings up a text view, that says,
pick a color, any color.
Currently red is being used as the default
selection.
Now suppose I want to select a different
color.
To do that, I'll click on the Spinner,
right now it says red, and that causes
the Dropdown with the list of colors to
appear, so now, I'll select the yellow.
The DropDown list disappears, the color
yellow now appears
as the selected color, and you can see the
separate
window showing the text, the color is
yellow.
And I can do it again.
This time I'll pick the color violet,
and you see the same behaviour occurring
again.
Now I'm back in the IED looking at the
UISpinner application.
I'll now open the Spinner Activity file
and go to the on create method.
First, there's a call to set content view
using the main dot XML Layout file.
Let's open that file.
Here we see that the User Interface has
several parts.
In particular, it has a Spinner element,
called Spinner.
And going back to the Spinner activity, we
now set up an Adapter for the Spinner.
We create this Adapter, the call to array
Adapter's createFromResource method.
The parameters to this method include the
list of colors, and a Layout for each view
that will appear in the Drop Down list.
Let's take those resource files now.
First I'll open up the strings .XML file
which holds the colors array.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Next I'll open up the Drop Down item .XML
file.
That has the Layout for the Drop Down
views.
And here you see that each color will
appears a
text to you, with the certain padding and
font size.
We're turning back to the Spinner
activity, next
few lines, set the Adapter, and then set
an On Item selected listener.
And that's called when the User selects a
color.
The next ViewGroup is the Gallery class.
This ViewGroup displays a set of data with
a horizontally scrolling list.
Like a Spinner, the data for a gallery
object, is managed by a Spinner Adapter.
Here, I'll start up the UIGallery
application.
As
you can see, the data for this
application, is a set of images.
And I can swipe on the display, to move
forward, and backward
through the list of images.
You'll also notice that when I select a
particular image, a listener is invoked to
display the Index of the selected image.